Hey there. Before we start, this video
combines together all my many A push
topic review videos without the AP style
questions at the end of each video. If
you'd be interested in trying AP style
questions associated with each topic, my
full A push review playlist will be in
the description. I just want to really
quickly note that earlier units in this
course might have a little lower editing
and audio quality. As the course
progresses, my editing and microphones
got way better, so just keep that in
mind. Anyway, let's get in to the entire
AP US history course review.
Topic 1.2 is all about societies in the
Americas before the contact of Europeans
on the continent. The starting thing to
know is that before Europeans came into
contact with America, there were many
societies that existed inhabited by
various Native American tribes. For this
video, you need to know how they lived
in the Americas. The crop of maize or
corn became a staple food of many of
these native societies, especially the
ones in the southwest, as the
cultivation of maze taught these
societies advanced irrigation techniques
and supported economic development. One
of the most notable tribes thriving from
this was the Hoha, who built extensive
canal systems for irrigation. In the
Great Basin and the Western Great
Plains, many tribes saw the dryness in
the area and lived by always moving
around and not making permanent
settlements. Examples of tribes in this
area were the Ute and the Shosani
tribes. The Northeast was much
different. The Atlantic and the
Mississippi River allowed for permanent
villages to be made with the societies
functioning on agricultural obligations
and hunter gatherers. A notable tribe in
this area was the Cahokia. And this was
actually very similar to the people in
the northeast in present day California
area as they also supported themselves
on hunting and gathering and used the
Pacific shoreline as a good place to
build settlements. with one of my
favorite tribes in this area being the
Shinuk. Last video we talked on
societies in the Americas before
Europeans came in contact. [music] Well,
Mr. Christopher Columbus arrives onto
America in 1492 and that changes the way
of history for the Americas forever.
Essentially, the various European
countries decided that they were going
to explore and conquest this new land.
The reasons for this are very simple.
It's the three G's, gold, God, and
glory. First Europeans wanted to gain
more wealth which was at the time
measured in gold and silver under a
system called mercantalism. Since there
was a lot of gold in the Americas,
conquering land allowed for mines to
open up and more wealth going to
European countries. The second reason
was that Europeans saw the native
civilizations in the new world and felt
a kind of religious obligation to spread
and convert the natives to Christianity
with a special effort from Jesuit
missionaries. Finally, there was glory.
Back then, the more land a country
controlled, the more powerful it was
considered. The Americas offered a new
frontier to claim and show off to the
rest of the world. Topic 1.4 is all
about the Columbian exchange and how it
impacted Europe and the Americas. So,
first we need to define the Columbian
exchange. By definition, the Columbian
exchange means the transfer of goods,
foods, animals, fauna, fauna, diseases,
and slaves between the Americas and
Europe after European contact in the
Americas. Essentially what happened is
when European countries came to America,
various things got transferred from one
continent to the other. The Americas had
revolutionary crops like maize,
potatoes, tomatoes and tobacco that got
transferred to Europe. The influx of
these foods to Europe caused there to be
a population boom and the transfer of
goods allowed for Europe to shift from
an economic system of feudalism where
land was owned by nobles and worked by
peasants to capitalism where trade and
industry are controlled by private
owners for profit. Also during this
time, maritime technologies underwent
massive improvements such as the Caravl
and Astrolab, meaning it was easier for
people to explore. What also made it
easier was the impleation of joint stock
companies. This was a company that a
bunch of people could pull their money
into. So if it did well, they would all
earn money. If not, they could only lose
their initial investment. So it was very
low risk. These joint stock companies
were the companies funding these voyages
to the Americas. As for Europe's effect
on the Americas, yes, there was goods,
foods, and animals brought to the
Americas like wheat, rice, horses, and
pigs. But the biggest thing that came
from Europe to the Americas was deadly
diseases. Europeans had been living with
diseases like smallox and measles for
many centuries and had gained a sort of
natural immunity to them. The natives,
however, did not have the same immunity,
and therefore, when these diseases got
introduced, it's said that 50 to 90% of
the native population died because of
them. Topic 1.5 is all about slavery in
the New World by the Spanish. In my last
video, I didn't go much into detail on
this, but along with goods, foods, and
diseases, slaves were also transported
during the Columbian exchange. The
reason for this was, well, we first need
to go back in time. When the Spanish
landed in the New World, they wanted to
harvest the goods and crops of the land
and therefore decided to enslave the
natives through the Encoma system. This
was a system where Spanish concistadors
were granted the right to extract labor
from the indigenous people living in a
particular area. In return, the
concistadors were to provide the natives
in this area with religious Christian
guidance and take care of their welfare.
However, in practice, these obligations
were often neglected and poorly
fulfilled. This enslaving of the natives
wouldn't end up working though for two
reasons. First, the natives knew the
land that they had lived on for
centuries better than their European
guests and therefore could escape pretty
easily. And second, the natives were
dying in mass numbers by smallpox, and
you can enslave a dead person. The way
Spain solved this was by transporting
slaves from Africa to the New World on
ships with the brutal journey known as
the Middle Passage and work the land.
This solved both problems because the
Africans wouldn't know the land and they
have the same natural immunity to
smallox that Europeans did. With these
many Africans on the continent, it
allowed for a cast system to form known
as the casta system where natives and
Africans were on the bottom and anyone
with Spanish blood was on the top. Topic
1.6 is all about different views in the
world during this time along with some
organized military resistances. So, it's
fair to say that any time in history
when an existing culture interacts with
a new culture, misinterpretations and
profiling will always happen from both
sides. [music] In terms of the natives
and Europeans, their cultures had
different worldviews on religion, gender
roles, family, land use, and power. Over
time, Europeans and Native Americans
adopted some useful aspects of each
other's culture. But as Europeans
increasingly attempted to enslave the
natives, different military defenses
from the natives happened. A few
examples of this were the Kapool
uprising in the Yakatan [music] and the
Tano rebellion in the Caribbean. And
even though documents like the Ricera
Miendo tried to justify harsh treatments
of the natives, it sparked debates from
around the continent of how Africans and
Native Americans should be treated.
Though these arguments did exist, any
arguments often led to Europeans
justifying their treatment of Africans
and the natives using culture or race as
an answer. Unfortunately, that is most
of what early US history is about. On
the screen,
topic 2.2 is about not just Spanish
efforts in the New World, but the
French, Dutch, and British efforts as
well. So, I should preface this all by
saying that the Spanish were not the
only ones in the new world, though they
were the forerunners. Other European
countries came in too after hearing of
the riches of the new world. Let's start
with a little review on the Spanish. So,
the Spanish find the new world and try
to enslave the natives under the encomam
system. This however faced criticism
throughout the country. So, in some
areas they replace their system to the
repart of Meento system, which was
supposed to be less exploitive and for
shorter periods. But it still led to
horrid conditions for the natives. In an
attempt to justify their colonization,
the Spanish forcefully converted a fair
amount of the natives to Christianity.
And after the slavery of the natives
didn't really work, they transported
slaves from Africa and enslaved them to
work under a system called Acento. Okay,
that's the Spanish's way in the New
World. Now, let's talk about the French
and the Dutch. They were a lot nicer to
the natives and sent few Europeans to
the continent and attempted to make
trade alliances along with marry some of
the natives in an attempt to build
economic and diplomatic relations to
export products like furs to Europe.
with the French making their great piece
of Montreal in 1701 and the Dutch
continuing to build their fur trade
empire through strategic alliances
focused on cooperation. And finally, the
English. English men and women migrants
like John Smith and John Winthrop were
attracted to the new world for four
reasons. First was social mobility as
they believed they could potentially
raise their social standing moving to
the new world. Next was economic
prosperity as colonists believe the
Americas were a gold mine where they
could potentially grow wealthy from.
Third was religious freedom as groups
like Puritans, pilgrims, and Quakers
were being persecuted in Europe and
especially England, causing them to seek
new grounds to worship freely. And
finally, improved living conditions as
the colonies offered a new life and new
opportunity that could be better than
living in Europe. Once the colonists
moved to the New World, English settlers
often took land from the Native
Americans, sometimes through treaties,
but more often through force. And the
colonies they created centered their
economies on agriculture, but more on
that next. So, we're going to have some
fun with this video all about British
colonies and how they functioned. But
before we get to that, I need to tell
you about English arrival into the New
World. So, the British come into the New
World and expect to find vast amounts of
gold in Virginia and along the Atlantic
coast. This ends up not happening, but
the Americas still offered the British
cash crops like tobacco and rice. So,
they end up making farms in their
various colonies. The people on these
farms were mostly indentured servants
who were English workmen and women that
in exchange for passage to the new world
they would have to work the land for a
set number of years which would normally
average around seven. Now this worked
for a while but after a while there was
a shortage of indentured servants along
with the growth of African slavery which
inevitably caused indentured servitude
to fail. Now to talk about the British
colonies I have for you a random woman I
paid off a fiverr to voice over this
part of the video. Hey there, FutureMax
here. Unfortunately, in this original
video, I used copyrighted music. So,
instead of that British lady, I'm going
to pop in and explain this to you
instead. Basically, your idea here is
that all British colonies are different
in some way. For example, the Chesapeake
Bay and North Carolina regions were
known as tobacco colonies, mostly
because the region got rich on the
laborintensive crop tobacco,
specifically relying on tobacco exports.
Originally, labor for this tobacco would
be grown by indentured servants. But
quickly once indentured servitude
declined, African slavery would mostly
take its place. Let's move over now
though to the New England colonies which
were settled by the Puritans.
Specifically here you had rocky soil,
meaning farms literally couldn't be big.
So instead we have small farms. In this
area we also see ship building, fishing,
and lots of trade. This will mean the
area is defined by lots of family-based
communities along with lots of religion
and tradition. Now let's move over to
the middle colonies such as Pennsylvania
and New York. These ones will
specifically be known for their grain
production, which is why you might hear
them be called bread colonies. These
colonies will be very diverse with
people like Germans, the Dutch, English,
and many more. Meaning there will be
lots of diversity and tolerance. The
last one we have here though are the
Southern Atlantic plus the British West
Indies colonies. These ones are going to
be your plantation economies where
you'll see cash crops being farmed like
sugar in the Caribbean and rice and
indigo in the south. It should also be
noted that most of the labor for these
plantations will be done by slaves,
meaning the majority of the population
in most southern colonies will actually
be African slaves. All right, that's it
for me. Let's get back to past Max, who
really needs to learn how to edit a
video better. Cheers, mate. One thing to
notice is how unusually democratic
British colonies at this time were.
Like, the New England colonies ran on
town meetings and the southern colonists
were ran by elite planters with elected
assemblies, which were basically unheard
of at the time. The most notable of all
is to talk about the Chesapeake Bay
colonies with a special emphasis on the
town of Jamestown in Virginia, which was
the first official permanent English
settlement in 1607 and was easily the
most popular of all English colonies
with its tobacco exports and its unique
government style. Topic 2.4 is all about
the transatlantic trade. The main thing
to take away from all of this is all
Europeans really wanted from the New
World was profit. crops in the new world
were so unbelievably profitable by the
Europeans that heck, there is an
argument that without the crop of sugar,
there is no African slave trade. And as
goods and slaves were being transported,
a system of trade known as the
triangular trade, where European ships
carried manufactured goods such as guns,
cloth, and alcohol to Africa in exchange
for African slaves to be transported to
the New World and have them undergo the
middle passage, which saw Africans
chained and tightly cramped together in
ships to the New World. And finally, in
the Americas, the enslaved Africans were
sold and the ships were loaded with raw
materials such as sugar, tobacco, and
cotton, which were then transported back
to Europe. As you can see, this way of
trade resembles a triangle, which is why
it's known as the triangular trade. This
trade would also cause diseases like
smallox to be spread to the new world
and syphilis to be spread to Europe.
Meanwhile, in North American colonies,
the British government continuously
attempted to incorporate their
monarchical and hierarchical structure
in the colonies for the point of earning
the most wealth, which would inevitably
receive push back from the colonists and
the American Indians. With one such
example being the Bacans Rebellion,
where after the governor of Virginia
refused to expel the Native Americans
from Virginia, a man named Nathaniel
Bacon rebelled and with a group of
around 400 followers tried to overturn
that decision and kill the natives.
Although the British suppressed this
rebellion, it highlighted the potential
for colonists to revolt, foreshadowing
the larger conflicts that would lead to
the American Revolution. It also
contributed to the decline of indentured
servitude. Just so you guys know, topic
2.5 is all about the interactions
between Native Americans and Europeans
and how it changed from my last video on
topic 1.6. The basic thing to know is
that even before European contact,
Native American tribes always fought
each other. Now we start seeing Native
American groups ally with European
countries in an attempt to once again
fight against other tribes. But even
though this did happen, we still see
Europeans expand and encroach on Native
American land. With a prime example
being Metacom's War, also known as King
Phillips War, which was the bloodiest
battle in American history relative to
the population of the time. This war
started because English colonists broke
treaties made with the natives and
continued to forcefully expand past the
natives land. and with the killings of a
few people along with some other reasons
the war began. King Philip was with the
Native Americans and fought against the
colonists along with a few Native
American tribes. In the end, it was said
that over 7,000 people died and the
colonists ended up winning. The effect
of the end of this war was the sort of
end of Native American power in the New
England colonies. Though most all Native
American resistances failed, there were
a few that succeeded. One of which was
the PBLO revolt where the indigenous
PBlo peoples successfully revolted
against the Spanish. The aftermath of
this was that it led to the Spanish
accommodation of some aspects of
American Indian culture in the
southwest. But this would end not really
mattering as decades later the Spanish
would end up taking the land of the PBLO
peoples. We already know that there was
a shortage of indentured servants and
therefore the British started
participating in the African slave
trade. The system that African slaves
were employed under the Spanish was
called acento. But in English colonies,
they were employed under a separate
system known as chattal [music] slavery,
where slaves were treated as property
and not people. These African slaves
worked heavily in the Chesapeake Bay and
southern Atlantic coast, but the
majority of them were in the West
Indies. As Chattel slavery became
dominant, the interracial relationships
between colonists and slaves became
illegal, which made Africans only breed
with other Africans, and new laws were
put in place that their children would
automatically be slaves. I know it's
awful. But even with this level of
hopelessness, some Africans rebelled
with an example being the first Maroon
War. But most that didn't rebel tried to
survive by maintaining their own
people's culture. One example of this
being the Gala community, which
maintained African traditions, such as
dancing to West African music during
their rare moments of relaxation. I've
talked a lot on slavery and the African
slave trade in colonies. And it's
because that slavery was a massive
aspect of colonies. In topic 2.7, we
move away from the connotation of
slavery and talk about other societies
cultures. The fact is in all European
colonies, there existed lots of
different religions and ethnic groups
causing acceptance of diversity in
colonies and the word for that is
pluralism along with varying degrees of
intellectual exchange. European leaders
saw their colonies in the Americas as
money makers and nothing else. The
actual truth was that these colonies
made their own unique culture and way of
democratic governance. European leaders
continued to clash with their colonies
on things like the navigation acts which
lowered trade with their colonies and
ended up hurting the colonies. The
enlightenment also started in Europe
which was an intellectual movement of
reason and science. This would have a
heavy influence on colonists later when
the revolution would start with the
ideas like freedom of religion and
equality. But in this video all you need
to know is the initial response to the
enlightenment in the colonies which was
the first great awakening. This occurred
in the colonies where it saw the revival
of Christianity in the British 13
colonies. This Christianity was
traditionally the British's form being
Anglicanism, but it shifted throughout
decades in the first great awakening to
branches of Protestantism like Baptists
and Methodists. We also see a rise in
the spread of Protestant evangelicalism.
The transatlantic prick culture also
started in the colonies where you start
seeing the communication via press. The
fact is that this culture had a
different way of life, government, and
reason that differed from European
thought. Europeans didn't really like
this and frequently clashed with their
colonies. That however is something to
talk about next. Unit
topic 3.2 is on the French and Indian
War, also known as the Seven Years War.
So to start this one off, I'm going to
ask a question. What was the First World
War? You might say, "Well, World War I
because it has a one in it." Some
historians, however, would argue the
Seven Years War was the First World War
because there was involvement from
countries all over the world. The fact
is this war is complex and was fought in
many theaters, but for AP US history, we
will only examine the US side of things.
This war started because of territorial
disputes, particularly in the Ohio River
Valley and mostly in the New World
between the British and the French.
British peoples were moving to the
colonies in massive numbers, and this
forced the [music] British to expand,
threatening French Indian trade networks
and American Indian autonomy. But let's
be real, this might be the official
cause of the war, but Britain and France
had had beef before this war, and this
was kind of the chance for them to
settle that beef. The French and British
had allied with many native tribes, and
so colony armies combined with Native
Americans would fight in this war. The
war started with a battle of the famous
Fort Necessity, [music] which the
British lost. Notice the number of
troops on both side of this battle. It's
very small. The only thing you should
maybe know about this battle is it
featured the general of George
Washington. In the nearly half of this
war, it's fair to say that the British
were heavily losing. [music] The French
just kept winning each battle and the
British were just sleepy. I mean, take a
look at the Battle of Mangahila. The
French had around 400 troops and the
British had,300 despite having three
times the manpower. Britain still lost
this battle because of their
conventional line infantry tactics as
opposed to the French and Indians
guerrilla warfare tactics. However, the
tide turned after 1758 as Britain
leveraged its superior naval power and
resources to gain the upper hand. Key
victories at Quebec and Montreal in 1759
and 1760 were crucial to their
successes. And finally in 1763 with the
signing of the Treaty of Paris, the war
ended. By this point in the war, there
was so many more forces than the
beginning. There are two big outcomes of
this war that you should know. First,
the French lost almost all of their
territorial claims in the Americas and
they were split up amongst the British
and the Spanish. The second is that this
war made both Britain and France heavily
broke. For Britain, this resulted in the
imposition of new taxes on the American
colonies. But I get ahead of myself. In
France, the financial crisis caused by
the war was one of the factors that led
to the French Revolution. After the
British victory, imperial officials
attempted to prevent colonists from
moving westward, and this generated
colonial opposition. While native groups
sought to both continue trading with
Europeans and resist the encroachments
of colonists on tribal lands. Now we
start talking about the causes of the
American Revolution, which usually
brings up two fields of thought.
philosophical causes and direct causes.
This video will be on the direct causes
being the British taxation. So the basic
question to ask here is with so much
diverse peoples in the colonies of the
Americas living different lives, how
exactly is this random group of people
going to come together enough to incite
a revolution? The answer is a common
enemy and a few other reasons. The
British had become heavily in debt
because of the Seven Years War and
therefore started taxing their colonies
in the Americas through acts. 1764 the
sugar act was passed where the British
taxed imported sugar. 1765 the stamp act
was passed which required colonists to
purchase stamped paper for any document.
1767 the towns hand acts are passed
which put taxes on imported goods like
paper, paint and tea. These three acts
finally started getting colonists to
think. The fact is the American colonies
were subject to British laws including
taxes but had no representatives in the
British Parliament to voice their
interests or concerns. The British
argued that they did have a voice by
proxy, but the colonists denied it. The
Sons of Liberty was a group who
boycotted and protested against the
British. The Stamp Act Congress
convened, where representatives from
several colonies met to formally protest
the Stamp Act. Also of note was efforts
of people like Ben Franklin, who helped
rally colonists into one united culture.
In 1770, continued British military
presence in the colonies caused the
Boston Massacre, where English soldiers
fired upon revoling colonists and killed
five. In 1773, Britain passed the Tea
Act, which put attacks on tea, which
everybody was drinking at the time. This
caused the Boston Tea Party, where
colonists dumped the tea into the
British harbor. This all led Britain to
passing the Intolerable Acts in 1774,
which closed the British harbor and gave
a hit to local governments. By 1775,
these issues along with others like
restrictions on westward expansion and
stuff we'll go over in next video, had
set the stage for the outbreak of the
American Revolution. The American
Revolution causes leads into two fields
of thought. philosophical and direct
causes. This video is on the
philosophical causes. So, if you
remember back in unit 2, I said the
enlightenment also started in Europe,
which was an intellectual movement of
reason and science. This would have a
heavy influence on colonists later when
the revolution would start. So, around
the same time all these taxes are being
imposed by the British, the
enlightenment is running rampant through
Europe. And because of the Atlantic
world, these enlightenment ideals get
spread to the British colonies. First we
have John Lockach who argued in his book
second treaties that every person is
born with a natural right to life,
liberty and property. And this might
sound familiar as this exact idea is
written into our declaration of
independence. Then we have Jean Jacqu
Rouso who argued in his book the social
contract that when people live under a
government they enter into a so-called
social contract where they give away
some of their freedoms for government
benefits. And finally we have Bon
Montescu who argued in his book the
spirit of laws that there should be a
separation of government into three
branches and there were plenty of
philosophes like Voltater and Hobbes who
argued against European government style
in favored a more republican style
government. This all caused colonists to
believe in the superiority of republican
forms of government and natural rights
of citizens. This is best illustrated in
a book by Thomas Payne named Common
Sense where he directly petitioned
colonists to declare independence from
Britain and also arguing that a
republican government based on the
consent of the people was the best form
of government and that the British
monarchy was tyrannical and harmful to
the colony's interests. And I want you
to think about this for a second. By
calling it common sense, Payne made
radical ideas like declaring
independence and rejecting monarchy seem
obvious and reasonable to everyday
colonists. All of this enlightenment
thought, including this book by pain,
would be engraved in the ideas of the
Declaration of Independence written by
Thomas Jefferson in 1776. These
philosophical causes combined with
British taxation set the stage for the
revolution. So, the stage is set.
Britain has levied many taxes on the
colonies and the colonist inspired by
enlightenment thought are reasonably
mad. In response to the intolerable acts
of 1774, the colonists convened at the
first Continental Congress to try and
solve the issue. However, then militia
men engaged with British troops in the
town of Lexington. And once those
British troops marched to the town of
Concord, even more militia men fired
upon them, forcing them to retreat under
constant guerilla style attacks on their
march back to Boston. The revolution had
begun. And understand that the colonies
didn't have an organized army. At the
second continental congress, colonists
attempted to fix this by establishing
the Continental Army. However, this army
headed by George Washington was filled
with militia men who had no formal
military training. England had been
established for thousands of years and
had an organized military and financial
advantages. Because of this, the first
part of this revolution saw the British
winning most every battle. Bunker Hill,
Quebec, Long Island, Fort Washington.
All of these battles saw the British
winning, but showed that colonists could
put up a fight. This especially is shown
in the Battle of Trenton, where
Washington's surprise attack after
crossing the Delaware River saw the
colonists win. It was also around this
time that Thomas Payne published Common
Sense and later America would declare
their independence. The fact is
throughout all these early engagements,
colonist morale was boosted and forces
kept growing in the colonies which
caused colonists to win more battles.
This all culminated in the turning point
of the revolution being the Saratoga
campaign. Throughout the entire early
part of this revolution, leaders like
Ben Franklin had tried to get the French
to join the revolution on the colonist
side. When the colonies won the battle
of Saratoga, this finally convinced the
French to join the revolution. Now we
start seeing the colonists along with
the now French victories in this
revolution. Stony Point, Newton, Kings
Melon, Chesapeake, all leading to one
decisive battle in the town of Yorktown,
where rough fighting for over three
weeks with a joint American and French
siege that trapped the British caused
the colonist to win. And finally, in
1783, with the signing of the Treaty of
Paris, the revolution was over with the
British finally recognizing America's
independence. And anyone can argue the
true reason America won. However,
looking at the troop numbers from the
beginning of this revolution to the end,
the one thing to take away is that it
was the colonist ideological commitment,
resilience, and assistance sent by
European allies that truly caused
America to come out on top. So, the
revolution is over. The question is,
what effect did it have on society?
Well, one of the things often glossed
over about the revolution is that there
were calls for abolition of slavery,
hence garning the name abolition
movements. The reason for this was
because of increased awareness of
inequalities in society and of course
the enlightenment which caused people
like Anthony Benze before and through
the revolution to continue writing books
calling for the abolition of slavery. It
did end up working but only in little
states like Pennsylvania where they
passed an act for the gradual abolition
of slavery which gradually got rid of
slavery in Pennsylvania. This was the
first act of its kind and set a
precedent for future abolitionist
movements. There were also many other
abolition movements in other northern
territories like Massachusetts. Women
played crucial roles in the revolution,
often working as nurses, seamstresses,
and managing households in their
husband's absence. This increased
participation along with enlightenment
inspired feminism orchestrated by
enlightenment thinker Mary Wilencraft
caused women to call for more expanded
roles in society. Abigail Adams in a
letter to John Adams pleaded for him to
remember the ladies and Judith Murray
and her on the equality of the sexes
used theology and reason to explain the
equality of men and women. This would
lead to a growing idea of Republican
motherhood, which called on women to
teach republican values within the
family and granted women a new
importance in American political
culture. However, women wouldn't start
getting true rights until the first wave
feminism of the mid-9th century. And
last thing to note is the American
Revolution's effect on the rest of the
world. Debt caused by the American
Revolution along with many other reasons
caused France to go through a radical
bloody revolution. Haiti being inspired
by the American Revolution and a lot of
other reasons caused a slave rebellion
in which they won. And once again, the
influence of the American Revolution was
a factor in causing a series of
revolutions throughout Latin America.
And though each of these revolutions had
their own modocum of reasons for
breaking out, the fact is the American
Revolution and its influence is a reason
for each one. So I'm sure you were
wondering how the colonies are governing
themselves after this revolution. Well,
first, states throughout the Americas
around the end of the revolution started
implementing their own state
constitutions, which typically placed
power in a legislative branch and kept
that only people who owned property
could vote. However, these constitutions
showed America was not unified and
rather a bunch of separate states.
Something called the Articles of
Confederation were implemented at the
Second Continental Congress. However,
states didn't really recognize it. In
1781, by the end of the revolution over
a ratification process of four years,
the Articles of Confederation finally
came into power. The Articles created a
central government for handling common
concerns of the states like diplomacy,
defense, and managing western
territories. However, [music] it was
internally weak to avoid the kind of
centralized authority that the colonies
had rebelled against. The federal
government created by the articles could
not enforce laws directly on the states
or citizens. It had no power to tax and
was largely dependent on state
cooperation. Despite its [music]
weaknesses, the articles did achieve
successes such as the Northwest
Ordinance of 1787, which set up a
framework for westward expansion. It
established guidelines for admitting new
states, promoted public education,
protected private property, and banned
slavery in the Northwest Territory. But
anyone could see that there was a
glaring issue with these articles. And
this would lead to our next topic on the
constitutional convention. Federalism,
an idea that combines a general
government with regional governments in
a single political system. The Articles
of Confederation was the original
attempt at being a federalist document.
The issue is is that it didn't maintain
a balance between states and the federal
government and gave states too much
power and this ended up making the
documents being weak. State
representatives all knew this and
decided to meet in 1787 at the
constitutional convention where they
would through negotiation,
collaboration, and compromise draft a
new form of government being the
constitution which made a more central
government. The actual details of the
constitution will be covered next topic.
For now, let's talk about this
convention. The idea of federalism
changed as a result of this convention.
The way it changed was articulated in a
document known as the federalist papers
written by Hamilton and Madison arguing
a strong central government was
necessary to create a perfect union and
to protect the individual liberties of
the people. So basically it was
condemning the articles that did not
achieve this central government. Then a
new group would pop up opposing this
imposition of the new constitution known
as the anti-federalists. People in this
anti-federalist group like Patrick Henry
and George Mason argued that the
constitution didn't address states and
individual rights enough. Because of
this, to ensure the Constitution would
be ratified, federalists promised the
addition of the Bill of Rights, which
were the first 10 amendments to the
United States. They emphasized
individual rights and explicitly
restricted the powers of the federal
government to appease the
anti-federalist groups. The best way to
describe the Constitution is Ben
Franklin's speech at the convention,
where he said he didn't approve of parts
of the Constitution, but acknowledged
that a perfect document would be
impossible, and this was likely the best
thing that could be made. However, there
was always one big issue, and from now
until 1865, slavery will be that issue.
The constitutional convention
compromised on slavery by doing two
things. First, they would pledge that
Congress could not prohibit [music] the
international slave trade until 1808.
Second, they made it so enslaved people
would count as 3-fifths of a person when
calculating a state's population for
representation in Congress. Hence, it
was known as the three-fifths
compromise. But understand that even
though slavery was such a glaring issue,
know that the word slavery was actually
never mentioned in the Constitution. one
today. The constitutional convention
though originally happened to change the
articles caused a new document to come
out of it explaining a new way of
government that is still used to this
day. It created a central government
that the articles lacked but also
allowed the powers to be limited to
embody federalism. There was still an
issue though. People from states with a
low population wanted an equal share in
voting rights in the country and people
in states with higher populations wanted
more voting rights because they had more
people. This is where we see the great
compromise of having the House of
Representatives based on population and
the Senate based on equal voting rights
to each state. This constitution saw the
implementation of three branches of
government that are all supposed to have
equal levels of power with the ability
to check the power of each other branch
with the judicial housing the Supreme
Court, the executive housing the
president, and the legislative branch
housing the House and the Senate. And
through a lot of different ways
explained in AP government, each branch
has its own specific ways of checking
powers of the other branches to make
sure one branch doesn't get too
powerful. And in this way we see the
constitution embodying the idea of
federalism very well. The constitution
is implemented and Washington becomes
America's first president shortly
followed by John Adams. During their
presidencies foundational institutions
were created to implement the
constitution such as the establishment
of the executive cabinet and the
judiciary act of 1789 which would
establish the federal court system
giving the judicial branch actual power.
Specifically Washington set important
presidents including serving only two
terms and establishing a tradition of
civilian leadership over the military.
In the early years of the Republic,
political leaders debated key issues
like the balance of power between state
and federal governments, economic
policy, such as the creation of a
national bank, and the proper approach
to foreign policy. These debates led to
the formation of the first two political
parties in the United States. The
Federalist Party led by Alexander
Hamilton favoring a strong central
government and pro- British foreign
policy and the Democratic Republican
Party led by Thomas Jefferson and James
Madison advocating for states rights and
pro-French policies. These parties would
cause separation that we even still see
today. Washington warned against this in
his 1796 farewell address where he
warned the nation against political
factions, fearing they would divide the
country. He also advised against
becoming entangled in permanent foreign
alliances, promoting a policy of
neutrality that shaped US foreign policy
for years to come. After the American
Revolution, the US government had to
navigate the continued presence of
British and Spanish forces in North
America. Britain specifically was
participating in an act known as
impressment where the British Royal Navy
forcibly seized men and forced them into
naval service. So once the Napoleonic
Wars broke out in Europe between Britain
and France, the US had to maintain
neutrality which was difficult due to
issues like British impressment on
American sailors and French demands for
US support under the Franco-American
alliance with the Federalists favoring
Britain and the Democratic Republicans
supporting France. Despite all of this,
the neutrality proclamation of 1793,
passed by Washington, officially
declared neutrality. Over back in
America, Spain expanded its influence by
establishing mission settlements in
California, relying on the labor of
local Native American tribes. This would
allow a cultural exchange around the
California area at the expense of Native
Americans. As American settlers moved
westward beyond the Appalachian
Mountains, they sought access to key
resources like the Mississippi River for
trade. The US negotiated treaties like
Piknney's treaty in 1795 which granted
Americans free navigation of the
Mississippi to secure territorial and
commercial interest. America was
developing itself in its early years.
But expansion westward would cause so
much conflicts leading up to a certain
war in 1861. But I get ahead of myself.
Now we're going to move to talking about
society and culture in the early society
of the Americas. In the years following
the American Revolution, a new national
identity began to form. Americans now
free from British rule wanted to define
what made them unique. In literature, we
see the work of people like Charles
Brockton Brown, whose wland became one
of the first American Gothic novels,
focusing on uniquely American fears and
experiences. The same search for
identity appears in Hector St. John de
Krebs, led us from an American farmer,
where he famously calls Americans a new
man, different from Europeans, blending
many cultures into something distinctly
American. This cultural shift wasn't
just about words, it was visual, too.
Federal architecture is a great example
of how Americans blended old European
styles with a new democratic aesthetic.
Take Garage Bank in Philadelphia,
completed in 1797. The building
represents strength and stability.
Religion continued to play a key role,
especially in regional identities.
Inspired by the first great awakening
and the revolutionary ideas of liberty.
Figures like Goan Pamplet, the first
known black Baptist preacher, founded
the first Baptist church in
Williamsburg, Virginia. His messages of
equality showed the ongoing struggle for
freedom and opportunity for all
Americans. Science and philosophy also
left their mark. The 1789 portrait of
Franklin by Charles Wilson Peele
highlights his status as a philosopher
and a scientist, depicting him with a
lightning rod, a symbol for his
contributions to understanding
electricity. John Trumbull's portrait of
Washington and William Lee showed how
painters crafted a visual narrative
celebrating the American Revolution.
These cultural developments reflect the
growing sense of national identity in
America even as regional differences
remain strong. The country's culture was
evolving from its art and literature to
its religion and architecture. I said
two things within my past videos. First,
I said slavery will be the big issue
until 1865. And second, I said westward
expansion would cause the Civil War. In
this period around 1800, we start seeing
the start of this. Migrants continuously
moved west searching for a new life. The
issue of this is that these migrants
were encroaching on Native American
land. This made Native Americans rethink
their alliance with the US and start
something known as the Northwest Indian
War and rebel with some examples being
St. Clare's defeat in the Battle of
Fallen Timbers. Even the federal
government had attempted to test its
federal power in this frontier tension,
imposing a violent whiskey tax and
prompting a rebellion against it. In the
expansion westward, Britain took the
side of Native Americans and provided
support against the US, which would
heighten tensions between the US and
Britain, which would eventually cause
another war to break out. The other
thing to mention is the growing split
between the north and the south. We
start seeing these two areas separate on
values around this time. The main reason
for this was slavery. The south had
slavery implemented heavily throughout
its territories and once they expanded
westward more slavery was implemented.
This caused various anti-slavery
sentiments to arise such as Gabriel's
rebellion where Virginia slaves rebelled
and it ended in a violent suppression.
Another example of this was the act for
the gradual abolition of slavery
mentioned in previous videos. But
overall, even with the split starting to
emerge between the North and the South,
lots of historians argue that this point
in history was when Americans were most
unified on the screen.
Topic 4.2 is about the age of
Jefferson's term in office. And really,
what just happened? So, Thomas
Jefferson, a diehard Democratic
Republican, takes office after the
Federalist rule of Adams. Continuing
into this period, we have these two
parties debating over relations with the
French and the British and powers of the
federal government. All things covered
in my topic 3.10 video. But we start
seeing debates over something new around
this period known as tariffs which is a
tax on imported goods meaning goods
coming into America. This tax is paid by
American companies which typically raise
their prices to accommodate for the tax.
Understand that in a world where the
south is typically known as a rural
agrarian expanse known for farming and
the north is known for their industries
and manufacturers. The south would be
negatively affected by these tariffs as
they need to import lots of goods
because of the lack of industries they
have. The north would benefit from this
tax as Americans would start only buying
American manufactured goods. The
Democratic Republicans hated the idea of
tariffs aligning themselves with the
South. The Federalists liked the ideas
of tariffs aligning themselves with the
northern view. During Jefferson's
presidency, he enacted the trade embargo
of 1807, which made it so America would
stop importing Britain's goods. This
would end up backfiring and hurting the
American economy. But possibly the most
famous part of Jefferson's presidency
was the case Marbury v. Madison, which
was a Supreme Court case that
established the concept of judicial
review, which allowed the Supreme Court
to review and invalidate actions taken
by the other branches of government if
they are deemed unconstitutional. And
another popular thing is even more
westward expansion. The US wanted the
land of New Orleans and negotiated with
France to get it. France offered the
entire Louisiana territory as they were
facing financial issues because of
Napoleon. And the US bought it for $15
million. Now, with all this territory,
the US wanted to map it. So they sent
Louiswis and Clark on an expedition with
the Native American guide of Sack Joa to
help them. They went all the way from
St. Louis to the Pacific and mapped out
the western territories and realized
truly how big it was. 4.3 starts talking
about tensions in the US economy and
differing viewpoints. Some war broke out
between Britain and the US in 1812
caused by British supporting Native
American tribes and impressment on
American sailors. It ended in a draw
with the Treaty of Gent that the US saw
as a win mostly because of the
nationalism caused by the Battle of New
Orleans. During this war, Federalists
met at the Hartford Convention
discussing disapproval of the war and
potential secession. After America quote
unquote won this war, this convention
would lead to the party's demise. And
that leads into the introduction of a
man who lots of people don't like,
including me, Henry Clay. This guy was a
lawyer, secretary of state, leader of a
future political party and so
influential in this period. He
introduced something known as the
American system. This was a response to
the war of 1812 and suggested to provide
national economic growth by establishing
a protective tariff, creating a national
bank and funding internal improvements
like roads and canals. This was so
controversial and caused many debates to
arise from the Democratic Republicans,
later known as the Democrats who opposed
it, and the new national Republicans,
later known as the wigs, who supported
it. The Supreme Court had its say with
its Molo v. Maryland case, which
established that federal power trumps
state power. But who cares about that?
It's time to talk about early civil war
causes. So throughout the early
republic, states kept getting added and
became either a slave or free state. As
this continued in 1819, there was a
bounce of 11 slave states and 11 free
states. But as America was expanding
westward, Missouri was added as a state.
The South wanted it to be a slave state
and it ended up becoming one. The North,
however, felt cheated and made the
Missouri Compromise, which added Maine
as an official free state and said above
a certain line there couldn't be any
more slave states. This shows the start
of weak compromises, creating tension
upon tension until eventual war. And how
about even more Civil War causes? The
Protective Tariff of 1828 put attacks on
imported goods, and the South was very
mad at it, even to the point they called
it the tariff of abominations. This led
to the South Carolina Exposition and the
nullification crisis, where the South
openly protested the tariff. There
likely would have been war if it wasn't
for Calhoun and Clay, who proposed the
tariff of 1833, which would lower the
tax over the years. But what this shows
is the South can and will revolt if it
doesn't like something, foreshadowing
the eventual civil war. Topic 4.4 Four
is about America's relations with other
countries throughout the beginning of
the 19th century. So, it's fair to say
America was struggling in this time to
create a global presence. Turns out
inciting a revolution to create a nation
doesn't get respect from other nations
that have been on the globe for much
longer. The US tried to rectify this
through things like the War of 1812. But
they needed more land. What they did
first was acquire Florida from Spain in
1819 under these two treaties. And they
also started a war where they forced the
seinal tribes out of the Florida lands.
The US also decided to prove their naval
might, which they did by inciting the
Barbar Wars against North African
states. But the big thing to talk about
is as America kept spreading westward,
there was more and more conflict with
Native Americans. Britain saw this as an
opportunity to support the Native
Americans against the Americans. This
would cause President James Monroe to
pass the Monroe Doctrine, which declared
to Britain that any involvement in
America by European powers would be seen
as an act of war. And to add insult to
injury, America also passed Mon's bill
number two, which prohibited French and
British warships from entering American
harbors. 4.5 introduces the market
revolution. The time of which great
innovation in mechanization,
agriculture, and commerce occurred is
largely called and known as the market
revolution, which is just a little part
of the larger industrial revolution of
the world. Inventions like the textile
machinery, steam engines,
interchangeable parts, the telegraph,
and agricultural inventions made
production methods of different products
so much faster and easier, causing
entrepreneurs to make a lot of goods and
businesses, causing people to buy more
goods, and you get the idea. One thing
to note about the market revolution is
the difference in evolution between the
north and the south. The north became a
place for all industries, housing all
types of manufacturing and businesses.
The advent of the cotton gin caused the
south to farm cotton furiously, making
the south grow up making mostly farms.
having slaves work at them and selling
the cotton from those farms for massive
amounts of money. Now, of course, the
south needed to sell these goods to
other countries mostly, but different
legislation and judicial systems support
of development of roads and canals and
railroads caused American regional
markets and selling to grow. This would
link the north and the south heavily.
But it should still be noted that no
matter how much the north and south are
connected in this time period before the
civil war, these areas were different on
values and culture and could not coexist
peacefully with one another. The market
revolution would also have a massive
impact on society and culture as well,
but that is a next video. 4.6 introduces
the societal and cultural impacts of the
market revolution. The innovations in
technology, agriculture, and commerce we
talked about last time didn't just make
goods and businesses. They changed how
people lived, worked, and thought about
themselves. Large numbers of
international migrants flooded into
industrializing northern cities to find
factory work. An example of a city
growing heavily industrialized from this
being Philadelphia. At the same time, a
lot of Americans moved west of the
Appalachians, building new communities
along the Ohio and Mississippi rivers,
with some cities growing here like St.
Louis and Cincinnati. This movement
created a new dynamic between regions as
the North urbanized while the West
focused on agriculture. Next, let's talk
about wealth and class. Manufacturing
growth led to higher standards of living
for some folks, creating a bigger middle
class and a wealthy business elite. But
it should be noted it also created a
large and growing population of laboring
poor who worked for long hours for low
wages in these factories. Life was
better for some, but definitely not for
all. As for gender and family roles,
with the rise of factories, many
Americans, both men and women, stopped
relying on farming to survive. Instead,
they worked to produce goods for distant
markets. This shift brought about new
ideas of gender roles. Women especially,
were expected to stay home and embrace
domestic ideals, which emphasized the
separation of public work life for men
and private home life for women. Not
everybody was happy about this. Hey
there, Future Max here again. I just
want to quickly note that for like the
next seven topics or roughly 10 minutes,
I was actually pretty sick while I
recorded those videos. The videos are
pretty good. Just know if I sound a
little bit different, that is why. Topic
4.7 talks about expanding democracy from
1800 to 1848. Democracy in America went
from being exclusive to rich landowning
white men to slightly less exclusive. By
the 1840s, almost all adult white men
could vote. So, is that progress? Kind
of. The big shift came with the
elimination of property requirements for
voting. Before this, you had to own land
to cast a ballot. But as more states
dropped this rule, voting rights
expanded and participatory democracy
became a thing. One key event you should
know is the Door Rebellion in Rhode
Island, where Thomas Store Door and his
supporters pushed for a new state
constitution to expand voting rights
since the original charter only let land
owners vote. Basically, more people got
involved in politics. However, it's
important to note this only applied to
white men. Women, black Americans, and
indigenous people were still left out.
Now, with more people voting, political
parties formed. The actual details of
these political parties will be covered
next video, but for now, all you should
know is that the whole political
framework of the 1820s up to the Civil
War was known as the second party
system. Boy, Andrew Jackson, we already
get to talk about such an amazing man.
And before I get canceled on Twitter,
I'd like to say that I'm using a rare
attribute called sarcasm. So, new
political parties emerged in the 1820s
and 1830s. On one side, you had the
Democrats led by Andrew Jackson, who
believed in a limited federal
government. Jackson was all about the
common man, opposing elites and big
government institutions. He famously
hated the national bank, calling it a
corrupt tool of the wealthy. He vetoed
its recharter in 1832 and moved federal
funds to state banks known as pet banks.
On the other side, you had the Wigs, led
by Henry Clay, who supported a stronger
federal government. Remember that
American system we talked about before?
Well, the Wigs loved it. The thing is,
the American system embodied every
single thing Andrew Jackson despised.
The debates on the American system
weren't just political. They shaped the
economy, infrastructure, and the
direction of the country. As expansion
roared heavily on the frontier, Jackson
backed the frontier settlers with
policies like the Indian Removal Act of
1830, which forced Native American
tribes off of their land. This led to
the Trail of Tears, where thousands of
Cherokee were forcibly relocated to what
is now Oklahoma, suffering greatly along
the way. Jackson's policies made him a
hero to many frontier settlers. But his
use of federal power sparked fierce
debates about whether the government was
protecting citizens or abusing its
power, especially when it came to native
lands in the economy. Topic 4.9 talks
about the development of a new American
culture. Between 1800 and 1848, America
wasn't just growing politically or
economically. It was developing its own
national identity. This new national
culture combined American, European, and
regional influences. In art, you had
movements like the Hudson River School,
which painted breathtaking landscapes of
the American frontier. It wasn't just
for art's sake. It symbolized manifest
destiny and the idea that American
natural beauty was something special.
Meanwhile, writers like Washington
Irving gave us stories like the legend
of Sleepy Hollow, blending European
storytelling traditions with American
settings and themes. But it wasn't all
spooky stories and pretty paintings.
Philosophy was evolving, too. Case in
point, transcendentalism, a movement led
by people like Ralph Waldo Emerson and
Henry David Thorough. They believed in
individualism, nature, and the idea that
humans could achieve personal
perfection. Sounds inspiring, right? But
it also had a political edge.
Transcendentalists were big on social
reform, especially abolitionism and
women's rights. On the darker side of
American culture, Gothic literature was
making its mark. The big person here is
Edgar Allen Poe with stories like The
Telltale Heart, which is literally a
story describing in vivid detail killing
an old man, dismembering the body in a
bathtub, and stuffing the body parts
under a floorboard. I mean, hats off to
this man. Finally, architecture played a
key role in shaping the national
identity. Buildings in Washington DC
like the White House and the capital
were designed with neocclassical
architecture inspired by ancient Greece
and Rome. This is because America wanted
to position itself as a modern republic
with deep roots in democratic ideals. So
the second great awakening, what is it?
Short answer, it was a religious
revival. But more than that, it was a
massive cultural shift that reshaped
American society and politics. So you
might be wondering what caused the
second great awakening. Well, a few
things. First was the rise of democratic
and individualistic beliefs. Second was
a response to rationalism because of
criticism of the enlightenment being too
rational-based. And let's not forget the
market revolution which uprooted
communities and made people more mobile
creating new opportunities for religious
movements to spread. Here's some
examples of parts of this movement. Camp
meetings became huge social events
especially in the frontier. Preachers
like Charles G. Finley led emotional
fury revivals in places like the burned
over district of New York where
religious enthusiasm ran so high it was
said that there was no one left to
convert. The second great awakening also
sparked major reform movements.
Religious leaders preached that
individuals could achieve personal
salvation and improve society. This
inspired people to tackle issues like
abolitionism, temperance, and women's
rights. Jireina Lee and Harry Hoyer
Hoer, we'll go with Hoer. Two prominent
African-American preachers challenged
traditional ideas by showing that black
Americans and women could lead in
spiritual life. And one more thing, new
religious movements emerged. Joseph
Smith founded the Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints or Mormons. While
William Miller's predictions about the
end of the world led to the formation of
the Adventist churches. So between 1800
and 1848, America experienced a wave of
reform movements that aimed to fix
society's problems and expand rights and
opportunities. First, let's talk about
what sparked these movements. The Second
Great Awakening played a huge role. It
wasn't just a religious revival. It
encouraged people to believe that
individuals could improve themselves and
society. This combined with a market
revolution and greater mobility made
people more interested in reforming
moral and social issues. So, let's look
at some reform movements. First up,
abolition. The abolitionist movement
grew in the north, calling for the
immediate end of slavery. Leaders like
William Lloyd Garrison published the
liberator, demanding freedom for
enslaved people. Meanwhile, free
African-Americans like Frederick Douglas
became powerful voices in the movement,
sharing firstirhand accounts of
slavery's horse. Then there was women's
rights. In 1848, reformers like
Elizabeth Katy Stanton and Locitia Mat
organized the Senica Falls Convention
where they called for the greater
equality of women. They even issued the
Declaration of Sentiments which borrowed
language from the Declaration of
Independence to demand women's rights to
vote. This caused this time period to be
dubbed the era of firstwave feminism.
The temperance movement aimed to reduce
alcohol consumption. Reformers believed
drinking led to poverty, crime, and
broken families. And of course, you know
that there's no way that's true.
Organizers like the Daughters of
Temperance pushed for laws to limit or
ban alcohol. Finally, utopian
communities popped up around the
country. Groups like the Shakers and
Brook Farm tried to create perfect
societies by rejecting traditional norms
and focusing on communal living. But if
there's one thing this course should
teach you, it is that life is suffering.
And of course, all of these communities
failed. In this time period,
African-Americans, both enslaved and
free, faced enormous challenges. But
they also created communities and
strategies to protect their dignity and
fight for freedom. So, what stayed the
same and what changed? In the South,
enslaved people continued to resist
their oppression, but their efforts to
end slavery were largely limited to
rebellions, and most were unsuccessful.
One of the most famous was Nat Turner's
rebellion in 1831. Turner, an enslaved
preacher, led a violent uprising in
Virginia that resulted in the deaths of
over 50 people. The rebellion terrified
southern whites and led to harsher slave
laws. Meanwhile, in the north,
abolitionist movements were growing. The
free African-American population
increased, especially in cities like
Philadelphia and Boston. Many
African-Americans founded their own
communities and institutions to preserve
their culture and fight for their
rights. For example, the African Meeting
House in Boston, built in 1806, became a
hub for education, abolitionist
meetings, and religious services. One
key thing African-Americans did was use
the press. In 1827, Freedom's Journal
became the first blackowned and operated
newspaper in the United States. It gave
African-Americans a platform to speak
out against slavery and challenge racist
policies. But you have to understand the
biggest thing that helped these
African-Americans was their own
spiritual commitment. Like for example,
enslaved people in New Orleans gathered
at Congo Square on Sundays to play
music, dance, and preserve their
cultural traditions. These gatherings
helped them maintain a sense of identity
and community even in the face of
oppression. So here's the line to take
away from this whole video. While
African-Americans faced harsh conditions
of discrimination, they found ways to
resist and fight for their freedom.
America, a beautiful country of glorious
cities. But there's really only one
place you can call perfect. That's
right, the American South. So, what was
the South like in this time period?
Well, first off, geography and the
environment shaped the South's economy
and identity. Southern land was perfect
for growing cash crops like cotton,
tobacco, and sugar. But there was also a
problem. Overcultivation. The soil in
the southeast became depleted. So,
slaveholders moved west, expanding
plantations into new fertile land in
places like Alabama, Mississippi, and
Texas. All right, enough beating around
the bush. So, slavery. Although most
southerners didn't own enslaved people,
the region's economy and leadership were
built on slavery. Southern leaders like
John C. Calhoun went from calling
slavery a necessary evil to defending it
as a positive good. According to
Calhoun, slavery wasn't just acceptable.
It was essential to the southern way of
life. This focus on agriculture and
slavery gave the South a distinct
regional identity. While the North
industrialized and diversified, the
South stayed locked in traditional
agriculture staples and resisted change.
Southern business leaders kept relying
on cotton exports to drive their
economy, which made the South heavily
dependent on both slavery and foreign
trade. So, what to take away from this
is the South became its kind of own
place and culture during this time
period. And this tension with the North
would, wait, say it with me, cause a
future war.
>> All right, it is the 1840s and Americans
are looking west. This idea that
Americans deserve and are destined to
expand across the entire continent that
is something known and called manifest
destiny and it was very popular in this
time period. So the big question is why?
Why did Americans think they were
destined to expand? Well, simply because
land equaled opportunity. The west had
resources, open land, and the chance to
get rich. Farmers saw fertile soil,
miners chased gold, and religious groups
like the Mormons just wanted to be left
alone in Utah. And if you want a city to
blame on that, you can look at Salt Lake
City. So, people just started packing up
and heading west. And when I say heading
west, I mean thousands of settlers
risking their lives on trails like the
Oregon Trail. Imagine walking 2,000 mi,
losing half of your wagon, fighting off
dissentry, and all you get in the end is
a nice view. But hey, for many it was
actually worth it. And that leads to the
one image that will always forever be
used to define manifest destiny. I mean,
look at that angel. It's as if these
people were meant to expand west. Or at
least that's what they thought at the
time. And the funny part is the
government wanted in on the expansion
too. To help settlers, they passed the
Homestead Act. Basically handing out
free land, that is if you could survive
on it, and the Pacific Railroad Act,
which helped build railroads across the
country. This made it way easier to move
west. But the US wasn't just looking
west. They were looking transnational.
Americans wanted more trade with Asia.
And in classic US fashion, they weren't
exactly subtle about it. The Treaty of
I'm not even going to try and pronounce
that, opened up trade with China. And
the Treaty of Kanagawa forced Japan to
open its ports to American ships. I know
I've said a million times that expansion
westward would cause the Civil War, but
before the Civil War, it will actually
cause a revolution and another war, but
that is a next video. So, it's 1845 and
James K. Pulk is elected president. If
there is one thing you should know about
this guy, it is that he cared only about
one thing. Westward expansion. He
started by negotiating with Britain to
secure Oregon up to the 49th parallel.
This would avoid war while expanding the
US northwest. But here's the thing. As
America expanded, tensions with Mexico
escalated over the Texas border. The US
claimed the Rio Grande while Mexico
insisted it was the new Cass River. Pulk
sent troops into the disputed Texas
Mexico border and after a skirmish, he
claimed quote American blood was shed on
American soil. He used this as a
justification to declare war in what was
known as the MexicanAmerican War. After
the US captures some major cities and
blockades Mexico, which cripples its
economy, they end up winning the war.
This war would end with the treaty of
Guadalupe Held in 1848. And while this
treaty did a lot of things, what you
should know is that it gave the US a lot
of land, like a lot of land. This land
was known as the Mexican session. And
the issue of whether each state would be
slave or free would need to be solved
further at something known as the
compromise of 1850. It should also be
noted that US interaction and conflict
with American Indians and
Mexican-Americans would increase because
of the westward expansion. These often
resulted in many unfair treaties or in
the case of Sand Creek, it would lead to
a bloody massacre where hundreds were
said to have been slaughtered in 1864.
So, the Mexican-American War just ended
and the US gained a massive chunk of
land. This land was known as the Mexican
session. But here's the issue. Should
slavery be allowed in this new land or
not? The North proclaimed no. The South,
however, said yes. So yeah, we have
another political crisis. There was an
attempt to settle this issue early with
something called the Wilmont Proviso.
This was a proposal to ban slavery in
all land gained from Mexico. It passed
in the House where the North had more
representation, but failed in the Senate
where the South had enough power to
block it. This failure only made
sectional tensions worse, pushing the
country closer to conflict. So what
would attempt to solve this issue would
be the compromise of 1850. But it was in
many ways a messy last ditch attempt to
keep the country from falling apart. The
guy behind it, you guessed it, Henry
Clay. This compromise had five parts,
and they all tried to balance free and
slave state interests. First was
California would become a free state.
Second is that Utah and New Mexico
territories got to decide on slavery
themselves through voting. Third is that
the slave trade was banned in Washington
DC. Fourth was a stricter fugitive slave
act was passed, forcing northerners to
return escaped slaves. And five, Texas
got paid $10 million to give up some
land claims. Yeah, I don't really
understand that one either. The big part
to know about this is the Fugitive Slave
Act made northerners furious. Even if
they weren't abolitionists, they hated
being forced to return enslaved people.
This led to massive resistance like the
Underground Railroad working overtime
and northern states passing personal
liberty laws to ignore the act
altogether. Meanwhile, in the South,
even though they got some wins from the
compromise, they still weren't happy.
They wanted an even bigger guarantee
that slavery would expand. The failure
of this compromise was easy to see and
this weak compromise is easily the
biggest cause of the civil war we have
talked about thus far. We already know
from the entirety of unit 4 that the
north and south at this time were
essentially two different countries with
the north being industrybased and the
south being farming reliant. So now
stuff is going to happen in Europe. A
series of revolutions break out in
Europe around 1848. And a potato famine
breaks out in Ireland, which causes tons
of immigrants from Ireland and Germany
to flood into the US, mostly all
settling in northern cities. They built
ethnic communities to preserve their
language and culture. But not everybody
welcomed them. But what you should
understand is truly how many immigrants
that came into the US. I mean, look at
this graph and it spiked there. Need I
even say more? All right, enough about
migration. Let's look at some
abolitionists. Even though abolitionists
were a minority in the North, they made
a lot of noise. As we've talked about
before, Frederick Douglas gave fiery
speeches, including What to the Slave Is
the Fourth of July? Exposing the
hypocrisy of American Freedom. Harriet
Beto wrote the book Uncle Tom's Cabin,
exposing the horrors of slavery, a book
that was said to be so influential that
Lincoln supposedly said it started the
Civil War. Harriet Tubman in the
Underground Railroad helped enslaved
people escape to the North. The North
and South weren't just disagreeing. They
were on completely different planets at
this point. immigration, economic
divide, and the fight over slavery kept
deepening sectional conflict, making war
almost inevitable. So, it's truly time
to examine the causes of the Civil War.
At this point, every compromise about
slavery has flopped. The Missouri
Compromise gone. The Compromise of 1850
made things worse. So, now let's look at
the final attempts to hold this broken
country together and how they
spectacularly failed. The Kansas
Nebraska Act got passed, which allowed
those states to freely vote on whether
they wanted to allow slavery or not. And
the funny part, that whole Missouri
compromise line from earlier, it didn't
matter anymore because Nebraska was well
above that line. But what you should
know about this act is it caused
thousands to pour into these states to
vote for their own side, which led to
what is called bleeding Kansas, where
everyone fought in the streets and
killed each other over votes in Kansas.
One of the people famous here was an
absolutely insane man named John Brown,
who was against slavery and staged a
slave rebellion at Harper's Ferry before
being killed by the expertise of Robert
E. Lee. The chaos of bleeding Kansas and
the spread of slavery enraged
anti-slavery northerners leading to the
formation of the Republican party in
1854. But now that we have all this,
let's contextualize and envision the
world right now. We know from the
Constitution that the US needs three
branches of government to function. So
let's look at each of them right now.
First, the executive. Leading up to the
Civil War, we see a collection of weak
presidents that did nothing truly
notable to address the issue of slavery.
Okay, so the executive branch is a
no-go, but let's try the legislative.
Well, here in the Senate, Charles Sunder
gave a speech against slavery, which
caused a southern congressman named
Preston Brooks to beat him within an
inch of his life with a cane. Okay, so
the legislative is a bust, but as long
as we had the Supreme Court, Dread Scott
be Sanford. God damn it. This case
established that slaves were not
citizens and Congress could not ban
slavery in southern territories. So, we
have the executive branch being weak. We
have people caning each other on the
Senate floor in the legislative and
deplorable, sadistic rulings by the
Supreme Court. When you look at it this
way, it honestly is hard to think a war
couldn't have broken out. And I'll end
this video with a quote from the most
sane, reasonable, level-headed guy I can
think of, John Brown. Right before he
died, he said, quote, "I am now quite
certain that the crimes of this guilty
land will never be purged away but with
blood." And guess what? He was right.
Because the Civil War started less than
2 years later. The stage is set. America
is on the brink of collapse. The North
and the South are done with compromises.
Sectional tensions are at an all-time
high. And now there's a presidential
election that's about to decide the fate
of the entire nation. America was so
divided at this point that four
different candidates ran for president.
First we have Abraham Lincoln for the
Republican party. He was against slavery
spreading westward but not planning to
abolish it in the South. Next you have
Steven Douglas who was a northern
Democrat. His idea was to leave
decisions in the hand of the people to
vote for. Then we had John C. Breenidge
who was a southern democrat. He was very
pro-slavery wanting it everywhere. And
finally, we have John Bell with the
Constitutional Union Party who pleaded
for the Constitution. Ah, who cares? But
the real issue, Lincoln's Republican
party was based entirely in the North,
and he wasn't even on the ballot in 10
southern states. But guess what? It
didn't even matter. He won anyway. The
moment Lincoln won, the South absolutely
lost its mind. They saw it as the
beginning of the end for slavery. South
Carolina didn't wait around. It seceded
just weeks after the election. By early
1861, six more states followed, forming
the Confederate States of America with
Jefferson Davis as their president.
Lincoln ran on a campaign that had at
its forefront to keep the Union
together. He promised not to invade the
South unless it was necessary to fulfill
that. In April, the Confederates decided
to enact the final straw and fired at
Fort Sumpter, a US military base in
South Carolina. Lincoln called for
troops to put down the rebellion, and
just like that, civil war had begun. So,
Lincoln is elected. The South secedes
and war is officially started. But
here's the issue. The Union and
Confederacy were nowhere near evenly
matched. The North had more people, more
industry, more railroads, and the
ability to outproduce and outlast the
South. The only thing the South really
had was better generals and a homefield
advantage. But don't discount this part.
The South had a population that was
willing to fight to the death. And
that's where the term a war of attrition
truly comes from. The first shots were
fired at Fort Sumpter, where the
Confederacy bombarded a US fort in South
Carolina. Lincoln responded by calling
for troops, and just like that, the war
had begun. But let's be clear, the Union
was not prepared. The first major battle
at Bull Run ended with a humiliating
Union defeat, proving this war wouldn't
be over quickly. So now we see two
different war strategies unfold. The
Confederacy's plan was simple. Hold out,
play defense, and hope Europe
intervenes. Meanwhile, the Union
launched the Anaconda Plan, a strategy
to blockade the South, control the
Mississippi River, and squeeze the
Confederacy into submission. The early
war saw Confederate victories, mostly
thanks to Roberty E. Lee and Stonewall
Jackson outmaneuvering Union forces.
Battles like Second Bowl Run,
Fredericksburg, Chancellor'sville, what
the heck are these cities, showed that
the South had a real shot at winning.
Meanwhile, both sides struggled on the
home front. The New York City draft
riots showed anti-war sentiment in the
North, while the Richmond bread riots
exposed the starvation and desperation
of the South. But then comes the turning
point, 1863. First, we have the Battle
of Gettysburg, where Lee tried to go on
the offensive, but got absolutely
pummeled in a three-day blood bath,
forcing him to retreat. And around the
same time, Ulissiz Srant won the Battle
of Vixsburg, giving the Union complete
control of the Mississippi River and
splitting the Confederacy in half. So,
now the war completely shifts. Grant is
promoted and he brings in William uh
Sherman, who introduces something known
as total war. This guy truly was
unbelievable. Sherman burned everything
in his path through Georgia, destroying
crops, railroads, and entire cities in
his quote march to the sea. Meanwhile,
Grant takes on Lee directly, hammering
the Confederates with non-stop battles,
knowing that the North could replace
soldiers, but the South really couldn't.
By 1865, the South was done. Lee
surrendered at the courthouse, and just
like that, the Civil War was over. In
the end, 698,000 people died. This makes
the Civil War the deadliest war in
American history. And no, we are not
counting World War I or two in that. We
talked about all the military stuff of
the Civil War. Now, let's examine the
political side. At first, Lincoln made
it clear this war was about preserving
the Union, not ending slavery. But as
the war dragged on, that changed. Let's
talk about how. By 1862, Lincoln knew
the war needed a new purpose. And after
the Union sword of victory at Antito, he
issued the Emancipation Proclamation.
This document freed enslaved people in
Confederate held territories, but not in
border states. It reframed the war as a
fight against slavery, not just union
preservation. And third, it kept Europe,
especially Britain and France, from
recognizing the Confederacy. Now, even
though it didn't immediately free all
enslaved people, it was a gamecher
because now thousands of formerly
enslaved people escaped plantations and
enlisted in the Union Army. By the end
of this war, nearly 200,000
African-Americans fought for the Union.
The first South Carolina Volunteer
Infantry Regiment in the 54th
Massachusetts proved black soldiers were
essential to the Union victory. After
the blood bath at Gettysburg, Lincoln
gave a two-minute speech that completely
redefined the Civil War. In it, he said,
number one, the war was about preserving
democracy and fulfilling the ideals of
the founding fathers. And number two,
the Union must win. So government of the
people, by the people, for the people
shall not perish from the earth. This
speech solidified that America wasn't
just fighting the South. It was fighting
for its identity. But I want you to
think beyond the political aspect for a
second. For black Americans all around
the country, this wasn't about some
simple politics. This was about having
the simple human right to live freely.
This is about being able to be treated
with just some dignity in their life.
This war was about freedom, democracy,
and most of all, national unity. The
Civil War is over. So many battles of
attrition along with various scorched
earth policies have caused the South to
be in ruins. Literally. Yes, the South
had lost the war, but now they were a
part of the Union again. So the
government tried to usher in an era
known as reconstruction to rebuild the
South. Originally during the war,
Lincoln issued his 10% plan that told
the South he would readmit a southern
state to the Union and give it America's
protection and benefit so long as 10% of
the voters pledge loyalty to him.
Lincoln's plan aimed to be lenient and
avoid punishing the South, focusing on
restoring the Union quickly. But then
Lincoln had to go and die in 1865 by
John Wils Booth, which upset quite a
bit. Andrew Johnson came in and gave his
plan which was very similar to Lincoln
apart from offering pardons to former
Confederates. Then later in
reconstruction, the radical Republican
plan was put into effect as Republicans
gained more power. This was meant to
punish the South, protect black rights,
and send the military to enforce it. The
South absolutely hated this. And the
thing is, Andrew Johnson hated radical
Republicans and tried to veto
everything. Congress responded by
impeaching him, making him the first US
president to almost be removed from
office. Reconstruction also allowed some
amendments to be passed as well. The
13th amendment which abolished slavery,
the 14th, which granted birthright
citizenship and equal protection under
the law, and the 15th, which gave black
men the right to vote. But even though
this seems like a good idea, you need to
understand that this era was really no
better for African-Americans than before
the Civil War. Almost immediately after
the southern states were readmitted to
the Union, they passed black codes,
which were codes in the South that
limited freedoms of African-Americans
and continuously forced
African-Americans into forced labor
despite slavery being technically over.
Blacks worked the fields in a system
known as sharecropping, where it wasn't
technically slave labor, but with their
wages, it might as well have been. There
would be public events held in the South
where people would gather to watch
African-Americans be hanged or tred and
feathered or any number of ways to die,
known as lynchings. And then you have
organizations like the Ku Klux Clan and
the White League which used literal
terrorism to suppress black voters. All
of this would force the North to just
give up entirely and cause
reconstruction to fail. But that is a
reconstruction was supposed to fix the
South and bring equality for all
African-Americans, but instead it
completely failed. At first, things
looked promising. Black men gained
citizenship and voting rights. Over
2,000 African-Americans held public
office and federal troops were stationed
in the South to enforce reconstruction
policies. But white southerners hated
this and they fought back hard. We
already talked about some examples of
this being sharecropping, lynchings, and
organizations like the KKK. But you also
had things like convict leasing where
black men were arrested for madeup
crimes and forced into unpaid labor.
Then came the Supreme Court, which
basically gave up on protecting black
rights. The slaughterhouse cases in 1873
gutted the 14th amendment by saying
civil rights were a state issue, not a
federal one. in the US v that they said
that the federal government couldn't
punish white mobs that murdered black
Americans. With no one left to enforce
black rights, white southerners took
control again. And then came the final
nail in the coffin being the compromise
of 1877. Essentially, the 1876
presidential election was a mess. So,
Republicans and Democrats made a
backroom deal. The North would remove
troops from the South, and in return,
they would elect a Republican Rutherford
Be Hayes as president. But this would
mean reconstruction would end and the
South could do whatever it wanted. So
that's exactly what happened. Black
rights were crushed for nearly a
century. Jim Crow laws, segregation, and
voter suppression took over.
Reconstruction was the US's first
attempt at civil rights, and it failed
miserably. But the 14th and 15th
Amendments didn't go away. They became
the legal foundation for the civil
rights movement 100 years later. on the
screen now. And really quickly, as we
are over halfway through this course,
consider subscribing to this channel and
potentially following my Instagram.
Totally up to you, though. Let's get
into unit 6.
Unit 6 is here, and we transition into a
new time period of American history. We
covered antibbellum, the Civil War, and
reconstruction, which are all viable
eras of American history. Now, we
transition into a new era called the
Gilded Age. This era will be explored
throughout this unit. But the biggest
thing to notice is that the US will
slowly start becoming controlled by the
rich throughout this era, not the
government. Of course, there will be
three big causes of this. Westward
expansion, the industrial revolution,
and capitalism. Right now, we will
simply talk about the westward expansion
part of it. So, let's recap. The Civil
War and reconstruction has ended. Yes,
this has left devastation all around the
country, but it also has left one other
big thing, an unbelievable level of
manufacturing. The big things here were
factories, steel, and railroads.
Railroads were especially exciting
because they could move a lot of goods
very fast, and the government made them
cheap to build. And that is why the
transcontinental railroad was ordered to
be built from the east to the west. Why
go to the west, you ask? It's simple.
Gold. So much gold was found in places
like modern-day Colorado, California,
Nevada, and many other places that many
settlers saw as a chance to get rich. It
also helped that at this time it was
really easy to move west because the
government still had the homestead act
in place along with various subsidies to
incentivize expansion. Farmers got a
bunch of new farming innovations like
barbed wire and steamed powered
equipment. And most importantly, the
west offered new land to farm and mine
on. With thousands of people moving
west, many communities formed. I
personally cannot be asked to go over
them, but here are some if you really
care to read about them. Now, here's
where things get muddy. Though there
isn't a technical start of the guilded
age, this is how the guilded age
essentially starts. There's only one way
a farmer or minor in the west is going
to transport their goods back to the
east. Railroads. The owners of these
railroads knew this and raised the
prices on everyone, especially small
businesses. This led to farmers creating
groups and alliances such as the
Graange, the Farmers Alliance, and the
Card Farmers Alliance. But remember what
I said earlier, the rich are in control
in this time period. And so it's no
surprise that all of these for the most
part failed. In this time period,
farmers relied on bank loans and the
influx of farming goods caused prices to
drop, making it so farmers suffered
quite a bit from debt. Remember, this
video is only one of three separate
causes of the guilded age. There are
still others you have to consider. So we
already know this settlers are moving
west because of gold, opportunity,
farming, blah blah blah. Now we are
going to talk about the effects of this.
So we already talked about the
transcontinental railroad. What we
didn't talk about was that the people
building this railroad were mostly
Chinese and Irish immigrants. And
understand that this was no easy job. A
very dangerous explosive called
nitroglycerin was constantly used to
blow out tunnels, and it would make it
very dangerous to work on these
railroads. Another thing to know is this
animal right here. In 1860, there were
an estimated 30 million bison in the
United States. By 1884, there were less
than a thousand. So, how the heck did
this happen? Well, railroads split the
herds. companies hired hunters to kill
them for hides. And the US military
encouraged killing them to force native
tribes off the plains. But that isn't
even talking about the worst part. Let's
look at our standard US map. West. Well,
what is west? Gold, obviously, right?
No, I mean the people actually
originally inhabiting the land. Yeah.
Native Americans still exist and they
are still trying to live freely in the
west. But by this point, Americans had
so many incentives to move west that
they didn't just ignore native peoples.
They actively despised them simply for
living on the land. Treaties that once
promised native sovereignty were
completely violated. America would
switch to a reservation policy and force
native tribes to live on specific
reservation lands. And this did not sue
many native cultures. So did the natives
fight back? Of course they did. It
started with Sand Creek, which was the
first major show of federal betrayal.
The Red River War ended native
resistance in Texas and Oklahoma. The
Nez Persece war ended organized
resistance in the northwest. The Apache
wars dragged on for decades but ended
when the Donimo surrendered in 1886. Now
there were native victories too like the
Sue Wars and the Battle of Little
Bigghorn but those winds were temporary.
Everything all came crashing down with
the Daw Act in 1887. This divided native
land into private plots giving the quote
surplus to white settlers. This led to
the loss of over 90 million acres of
native land. And around the same time, a
spiritual movement called the ghost
dance spread among tribes. It symbolized
hope for a world without white
domination. And of course, the US white
dominated military saw it as a threat.
And it all culminated in the Wounded
Knee Massacre. This would kill 300
natives and end the so-called Indian
Wars across America. The Indians being
the obvious losers. If you can't tell,
America are not the good guys here. They
took land they promised not to take and
killed thousands in the process. In
fact, if you live in any of these
states, you are living on technical
stolen land as we speak. It's
unfortunately one of the darkest parts
of American history. It's been a while
since we've talked about them. So, let's
go check on our good old friends, the
South. We've known up to this point that
the South has an economy that is
essentially entirely based on
agriculture. And up until the Civil War,
that agriculture was essentially all
done by slaves. So now when the war and
reconstruction are over, a journalist
named Henry Grady sees this and starts
petitioning the South to modernize and
adopt the industrial practices of the
North and turn themselves into a quote
new south. Now this does gain attention.
The North funds the South to build
mills, mines, and factories and big
industrial cities form such as Charlotte
and Atlanta. But even with all this
industry getting introduced, this quote
new south will continue to rely on
farming and sharecropping for its
primary economic base. So on the
surface, the new south is marked by a
switch to industry when in reality
agriculture still remains the primary
economic driver. However, the other part
to this is the role of African-Ameans.
And this is where you see the big
contradiction of the new south. Because
while the south talked to big game about
modernization and progress, socially and
politically, it was still stuck in the
past. White supremacy didn't disappear
at all. And the clearest example of this
is the Supreme Court case Py v.
Ferguson, which ruled that racial
segregation laws known as Jim Crow laws
were constitutional as long as
facilities were quote separate but
[music] equal. In practice, this whole
separate but equal thing never actually
worked out. African-Americans constantly
received worse facilities, fewer
resources, and almost zero legal
protection. Convict leasing, lynchings,
pole taxes, and unfair literacy tests
were all still very common across the
South. Now, there were people who
advocated for African-American rights,
such as Booker T. Washington who
emphasized economic self-help and
education and journalists like Ida B.
Wells directly challenged lynchings and
racial violence. But with these Jim Crow
laws now being considered
constitutional, it would be hard for any
real civil rights to appear until quite
a bit later. So the Gilded Age, when I
see this era of American history, what I
think of is governmental corruption, big
business, and disgustingly rich people
having power over the government. All
that stuff we will get to in our next
topic. But for this topic, what we need
to talk about is the sheer amount of
industrialization that happened during
the Gilded Age. You might remember the
market revolution. In the early 1800s,
you had people making machines. During
the Gilded Age, you now have machines
making machines. In the past, industry
relied on iron. Now, with the Bessemer
process, steel is what takes over. In
the market revolution, factories ran on
steam. Now, everything runs on
electricity and it transforms
production. And the other part of this
is now with all this new railroad
expansion, the US has access to so much
land and that land is a literal gold
mine of resources such as coal, iron,
oil, timber, copper, etc. But anyway,
you see what's happening here. We have
so many resources and a lot of new
innovations. This will make large-scale
businesses. These businesses will become
extremely popular. The people owning
these businesses will get really rich.
The US will stand down and adopt a lair
capitalist economic policy. And there
you go. That's the Gilded Age coming to
life. In a previous video, I said the
three causes of the Guilded Age were
westward expansion, the industrial
revolution, and capitalism. We already
covered the West, so now it's time to
talk about the other two. Starting with
the industrial revolution. And when I
say the industrial revolution, I mean
the second industrial revolution. And
even though that's considered a more
European term, with how much
industrialization happened during the
Gilded Age, it is fair to call what
happened a second industrial revolution.
During the guilded age, all the new
technology led to businesses wanting to
capitalize on the production or rather
the mass production of the goods. There
was a really big workforce because of a
bunch of new immigration and the
government policies heavily favored
businesses. And that is where we get to
throw in a key term, industrial
capitalism. This is where private
individuals own the means of production
like factories and machinery to generate
profit through wage-based labor by
mass-producing goods. Since this would
be popularized, it would mean the
capitalist lzas afair economic system
would become mostly standard in the
United States, meaning that it is the
third cause of the guilded age. Now we
turn to the consequences of this
industrial expansion which facilitated
the rise of three dominant corporate
figures of the guilded age. John D.
Rockefeller, Andrew Carnegie, and JP
Morgan. Rockefeller was probably the
richest man in American history. He
coined horizontal integration where he'd
buy out all of his rivals and he led the
oil industry. Carnegie on the other hand
coined vertical integration where he
controlled each and every means of
production and led the steel industry
and Morgan's the bank guy meaning he
controlled like finance or something.
Stuff like trusts were set up along with
many companies holding stock in other
companies known as holding companies
which resulted in entire industries like
oil and steel to be completely
monopolized. And these businesses would
even seek out markets outside of America
in all of these places on the screen.
And this would be the economic prelude
to American imperialism. As for the
government, initially what we see are
weak Supreme Court decisions and the
poorly enforced Sherman Antirust Act,
which meant the government really
couldn't do anything to combat this
guilded age. And yes, it is definitely
fair to say that these corporate giants
to use their deep pockets to influence
American politics. So, you might ask,
what is the result of all of this? Well,
I'll tell you. This would cause a
disproportionate share of American
wealth to be accumulated amongst a very
few top elite. Small businesses now
don't stand a chance. Monopolies would
cause prices on goods to go up, and most
of all, workers would be paid horribly
in these factories and had almost no
power to bargain otherwise. Very
quickly, this will cause these quote
captives of industry to be referred to
as robber barons because honestly, that
is kind of what they are. This would
lead to a movement later known as
progressivism, but I get ahead of
myself. So, it's time to talk about the
societal impact of the guilded age. And
to put it into perspective, I will say
three things that will be hard to
believe. During the guilded age, prices
on goods mostly went down. Workers real
wages actually increased and most
people's standard of living actually
improved. So that sounds great, right?
Wrong. Yes, mass production lowered
prices. And yes, wages rose on paper,
but that didn't mean workers lived well.
Most industrial workers earned barely
enough to survive, lived in overcrowded
tenement housing, and worked brutal
hours in unsafe factories. And cheaper
goods don't matter much when your life
is already miserable. Yeah. So, why
don't we play a fun game? Now, I imagine
most of my audience consists of the
typical teenage target worker. So, let's
compare what labor is like for a
modern-day Target position compared to a
Gilded Age factory position. Well,
first, at Target, you are only allowed
to work 8 hours a day. I mean, it's
standard, obviously. Now, moving over to
the Gilded Age. Yikes. That's rough,
buddy. But, okay. Okay. At least Target
has the ironclad rule of no child labor
for anyone under the age of 16. Oh, but
what's with all these photos during the
guilded age of kids working? It's almost
as if in the past child labor was
extremely common. But don't worry, at
least at Target, you're not going to get
horribly injured. And if you do, you'll
at least have workers comp to pay for
it. Well, here's the guilded age.
That's right. There are no safety
regulations, frequent injuries, child
labor, no workers comp, long hours, no
breaks, no helmets, no guards, no
warnings.
>> 5 minutes later. So, you get the idea.
Because of these horrid circumstances,
some workers united together into unions
that would protest this. Here are a few
examples. The Knights of Labor was a
union who accepted people of all skills,
genders, and races. They argued for
8-hour work days, no child labor, and
equal pay. It's too bad that they were
horribly unorganized and they were also
unfortunately blamed for this next
thing, the Hey Market affair. The story
goes, workers were protesting against
police violence against workers. One
thing led to another. Someone threw a
bomb and there you go, 11 people died.
And finally, the Pullman company's
workers went on strike. The big deal
with this one is that it showed complete
obvious proof that the government would
side with businesses over the common
citizen. So yeah, early on workers are
still going to be under horrible
conditions. But don't worry, there is a
reason the next era is called the
progressive era. So there is a big
workforce in all of these factories. So
you might wonder who exactly comprises
this workforce. Simply put, it's mostly
immigrants. Like obviously there are a
lot of prim and proper Americans in the
batch, but it was mostly immigrants. To
basically oversimplify this, not just
America, but the entire world is getting
privy to the knowledge of all the jobs
available in the United States. And a
lot of people wanted to come over and
start a new life. And also it helped
that life in these immigrants homelands
were not really that great, especially
if they were uniquely religious. The two
big waves of immigration you'll see are
people coming in from Europe to the east
coast and those coming in from Asia on
the west coast. This will lead to the
formation of two big hubs of immigrant
processing. Ellis Island right outside
of New York City and Angel Island right
outside of San Francisco. So let me
quickly explain something. If you're an
Uncle Sam American in this time period
with your own twisted racial beliefs on
the Ellis Island side, of course you're
going to want the lovely, hardworking,
mostly white Europeans in America
because they will create a better
society. But those Asians on the Angel
Island side, um, uh, so yeah, what I
mean is that in this time period, Ellis
Island was known as very welcoming. It
even had health checks and was seen as a
mostly great place. Angel Island, on the
other hand, was home to countless
interrogations, detentions, and long,
long stays, all instigated by deeply
rooted anti-Asian racism. And though
unrelated, here's a picture of me many,
many years ago on Angel Island. There's
no real historical significance here. I
honestly just wanted to show off that
I've been there. Anyway, the outcome of
all of this immigration is the formation
of lots of ethnic inclaves. This era is
the pure reason why there are things
like Chinatowns, Little Italies, Jewish
neighborhoods, and much more ethnic
areas around the US. We also see a lot
of internal migration in this time
period as well. For example, you have
lots of people from the rural
countryside moving into urban cities.
And finally, a bunch of
African-Americans are moving out of the
south cuz honestly, screw that goddamn
place. This would set the stage for
something later known as the Great
Migration. I think it's fair to say that
all the immigration coming into the
United States during this guilded age
was not that wellreceived by American
society. America has mostly always stood
on the principle of the acceptance of
any sort of immigration. At least that's
what they say on the surface. Behind the
scenes, there was a lot of debates and
quite a bit of governmental action as
well. So, let's give a few examples.
First of all, do you remember all those
Chinese immigrants that risked their
lives to do dangerous work building the
transcontinental railroad? Well, here's
a fun story. There was so much
anti-Asian racism that by 1882, America
passed the Chinese Exclusion Act that
put a 10-year ban on any new Chinese
labor immigration. But you also have
good things, too. Like, for example, in
the Supreme Court case US versus Wong
Kim Arc, it established and solidified
birthright citizenship, meaning anyone
born in the US is a US citizen. A good
book to reference here might be Rose
Cohan's Out of the Shadow. This book
follows the tale of Rose who immigrated
into the US as a Jewish immigrant and
shows her struggles to maintain her
culture as she worked through countless
sweat shops. Another thing to note here
is the work of women or more
specifically one woman named Jane Adams.
She's known for doing quite a lot of
stuff but for this time period what you
should know is that she co-ounded the
famous whole house where she would aid
the poor along with immigrants. Also
during this time you have people all
over the place wanting to justify their
class, race or just status in society.
And this is where an ideology takes hold
known as social Darwinism. Essentially,
what this means is applying the quote
survival of the fittest ideal to
society. Or for a better definition,
social Darwinism argues that the strong
naturally dominate the weak and that
social inequality, racism, and
imperialism are justified as natural
outcomes of competition. Now, of course,
I'm not even going to get into how this
is completely wrong and how it
completely misapplies Charles Darwin's
original thinking. Rather, I just want
you to know that this very controversial
ideology was used in this time period to
justify the success of those on top of
the social ladder. And like throughout
this entire unit, all I've done is talk
about how the rich are living gray and
the poor are not. And yes, that is true.
But there are quite a few people outside
of the top of the top and the bottom of
the bottom that actually benefited from
the guilded age. This group of people
would be the new emerging middle class.
Let me tell you why this middle class
actually formed. Going back to this
triangle, you have the ultra rich up at
the top and the povertystricken factory
workers at the bottom. But those weren't
the only two jobs that were needed in
this era. Big businesses like factories
also require a lot of white collar work,
meaning things like managers,
accountants, clerks, typists,
secretaries, salespeople, etc. were
needed. And these jobs paid better than
factory work and were way safer. Most of
the clerical work that was available at
a lower level will actually mostly be
taken by the women in society. The other
thing this ties into is education. Lots
of these jobs require a formal education
to understand them, which is where the
moral act of 1862 comes in. This act
gave federal land to states. And in
exchange, the states would use the land
to build institutions like colleges to
teach all the skills needed for these
white collar jobs. This is where we
start seeing teacher training or
business education and a new importance
to professional credentials. And also,
since there's now actually a decent
amount of people in the middle class
with disposable income and leisure time,
the first modern consumer culture
develops, things like amusement parks
such as Coney Island or maybe department
stores or a plethora of other things.
Also, let's talk about the rich really
quickly. Social Darwinism argued that
inequality between the rich and the poor
is natural, which mainly just gave poor
people another reason to resent the
wealthy. So specifically, one man, my
boy Andrew Carnegie, saw this and
decided to create a new ideology and
called it his quote gospel of wealth.
This book doesn't reject anything new.
In fact, it openly accepts inequality,
capitalism, and elite dominance as
natural. What it does differently is add
a moral responsibility. The big argument
of this book is that the rich deserve
their wealth, but they must use it
wisely for the public good. And believe
it or not, it for the most part actually
works. This idea will cause
contributions that create libraries,
universities, museums, hospitals, and
lots more urban improvements. So, at
least one person on our big three list
is doing good for the world. Just one,
though. This video is not about the
progressive era. It does kind of
establish the roots to the later
progressive movements, but we aren't
quite there yet. The big idea with this
topic is obviously with these horrible
societal inequities, there are going to
be lots of people beginning to push for
reform. This will typically split into a
lot of groups. We're going to talk about
each of them. To start off, socialists
and radical labor leaders like Eugene B.
Debs argued that capitalism exploited
workers and that major industries should
be publicly owned. This group was linked
to many strikes such as the Pullman one
talked about in a previous video. Then
you have the social gospel movement.
People like Washington Gladen will argue
for a religious response to poverty.
They argued Christianity should address
inequality, labor conditions, and urban
poverty. And finally, you have the
utopians, agrarians, and critics. These
movements were less important
individually and had similar arguments,
which is why I'm lumping them all
together. They pretty much all
criticized monopolies, wage labor, and
urban misery. All right, moving on.
Let's talk about women. We already
talked about Jane Adams and her whole
house, but you have to understand in
this time period, women couldn't vote
and had very limited legal power. So, a
response you'll see to this is the
constant use of voluntary organizations
to exert influence. Yes, you have the
reformers and yes, you have the
organizations, but you see a common
trend of what most women in these
organizations were pushing for.
Temperance, child labor reform, public
health, education, and anti-ynching
activism. Time to talk about some
macroeconomic principles, meaning we're
going to switch over to my lovely
economics background. Man, this
background brings back so many memories
of when I actually tried to review AP
economics on this channel. Got to say,
glad I didn't finish those courses.
Anyway, let's talk about what the term
LZ fair means. When I plug it into
Google Translate, it literally means in
French, let it happen. And this actually
perfectly explains the concept. If you
are adopting a LZ fair mentality, it
means you are taking a hands-off
approach. You don't intervene at all and
let all problems get solved without any
intervention. Moving back over to our
history background, there were
increasing debates over whether the
government should be involved in
regulating businesses and had a hand in
their own economics. And I'm sure you
can guess the result. The US will choose
to adopt a lzair mentality. However, you
do see attempts to intervene like the
Interstate Commerce Act and the Sherman
Antitrust Act, but those governmental
actions will be poorly enforced. In
fact, a good example to counter these
points is President Grover Cleveland's
veto to sending relief to farmers. This
shows the US actively refusing to help
their own economy in hardship. But
here's your contradiction, because while
the US government didn't intervene at
home, they definitely intervened around
the world. The point is, the US wants
more markets and more resources. Your
two examples to memorize here is the US
attaining the lovely Hawaii and Alaska.
Hawaii was attained for access to the
sugar industry and Alaska was attained
for its positioning and resources. There
are also other examples, but you don't
necessarily need to know them all. To
close out this unit, we're going to talk
about politics. Throughout US history,
we've gone through many political
parties. For the guilded age, the US has
settled on the Republicans and
Democrats. Republicans were strongest in
the North, were often backed by big
businesses and industry, and supported
high tariffs along with gold standard
currency. Democrats were strongest in
the South. They often drew support from
farmers and immigrants, and they liked
low tariffs, and they were more likely
to support something like free silver as
the currency system. The ironic part
here is that these parties actually had
a lot similar to one another. They both
were pro business. They both avoided
major reform. They both still relied on
Civil War loyalty for votes. And most of
all, they both were horribly corrupt.
Let's zoom in on the corruption.
Something called political machines
traded jobs and aid for votes,
especially in immigrant neighborhoods.
Now, they were corrupt, but they also
filled a welfare gap the government
ignored. A good example of this was
Tamonn Hall in New York City. The
Pendleton Civil Service Act tried to fix
this by creating merit-based federal
jobs. But even with this, distrust in
government still stayed high. And this
is where some agrarian activists will
form the people's party or rather better
known as the populist movement. Pretty
much this movement will argue that the
government should protect ordinary
people, not corporations. That means
free silver, a graduated income tax, a
regulation on railroads, and a lot more
things will be argued for. A democratic
leader who championed key populist
ideals is a man named William Jennings
Bryan. He's best known for his famous
cross of gold speech where he argued
that ordinary Americans shouldn't be
quote crucified upon a cross of gold,
condemning the gold standard and calling
for free silver to expand the money
supply. Now, this speech is a little
complex to understand, but to simplify
it, all he was really trying to do is
expand money policies to try and help
farmers and laborers. So, basically, the
common citizen. Now, even though
populists won't be elected for any
presidential elections, you will see
their ideas come up again in
progressivism and the New Deal.
To start off this unit, before
progressivism in US history, there will
be a very brief era of imperialism.
Imperialism here will simply mean that
the US will go out and try to take other
land and as a result become a world
global power. We already talked about
little examples like Hawaii and we'll
get to the big example next topic. For
now, we need to talk about debates over
imperialism because you have the side of
people who supported imperialism and the
side who didn't. This will be all we
cover this topic. So let's try to go
through this debate as fast as we can.
Imperialists or those who support
imperialism will have mostly four
arguments. One, economics because
imperializing will lead to new markets
and resources. Two, power politics
because Europe was colonizing and the US
didn't want to fall behind. Three,
racism/ a quote civilizing mission
because of the belief that white
Anglo-Saxon Protestants or wasps should
quote uplift others. And finally, four,
the frontier was closed. This idea was
caused by the 1890 census signaling
westward expansion was basically over.
Examples of people in this group are
Alfred theor Mahan and Josiah Strong.
Moving on to the anti-imperialists. They
will have three arguments. One,
self-determination, meaning the idea of
being an empire contradicts US
Republican ideals and the literal
Declaration of Independence. Two is
racism because people on this side
didn't really want non-white people
added to the US. And finally, three,
isolationism. They argued Americans
should keep their focus at home and
avoid overseas entanglements. A group to
reference here might be the
Anti-Imperialist League. And a few
people to note might be Andrew Carnegie
and Mark Twain. But for America's brief
little moment of imperialism at the end
of the 19th century, its biggest
campaign will easily be the
SpanishAmerican War. This war isn't like
many wars I'm sure you know.
Essentially, it started because Cuba
didn't want to be controlled by Spain
anymore, and the US was willing to
support Cuba in that regard. Propaganda
was also a big part with the growth of
yellow journalism. And the other part to
this is the sinking of the US ship, the
USS Maine. Now, it's not actually truly
known what really caused the explosion
that sank this ship, but it didn't
really matter because US propaganda at
the time blamed it on Spain. As for the
war, it was actually quite quick. The US
will fight Spain and the war will be
fought in Cuba and the Philippines, and
the US Navy will crush Spain quickly.
The decisive battle of this war will be
the Battle of Manila Bay. And a big
propaganda group that will get traction
here is the Ruff Riders, which was led
by Theodore, or better known as Teddy
Roosevelt. This war will end with a
treaty that we will happily add to our
list of the many Treaty of Parises. This
treaty will cause Spain to give up
Puerto Rico, Guam, and the Philippines.
Puerto Rico will quietly become a US
territory. Guam will quietly become a US
naval base, and the Philippines will
become a colony of the US for $20
million. But they will not go quietly at
all. This will trigger a
PhilippineAmerican war where Filipinos
led by Alio Aguinonaldo will want
independence and the US will suppress
this nationalist movement severely. As
for Cuba, it will technically be
independent, but basically the US will
have a shitload of soldiers occupy the
country and impose a controlling plat
amendment. So, I'll leave the debating
up to you whether or not that's truly
independent. The other outcome of this
war is that the US will finally be
involved with Asia and open up a lot of
trade with different Asian countries
like China. Welcome to the progressive
era. Yes, it's truly time to talk about
the era following the guilded age. Let's
quickly define the progressive movement
in one sentence. Progressives responded
to political corruption, social
injustice, and economic inequality
created and heightened by industrial
capitalism and urbanization. And I don't
want you to sit there and think this
progressive movement was one big unified
group because it really wasn't. Rather,
it was a bunch of little movements that
had a lot of things in common, which is
why we roped them together into one big
progressive movement. Reformers were
often middle to upper class and many
were women working especially in cities
and among immigrant populations. The
biggest thing you'll see in this
movement is something called muckreers.
This means a journalist/riter whom
investigates wrongdoing. Let's go
through some key figures in this regard.
Upton Sinclair was a muckreaker who
wrote the famous the jungle. This book
exposed disgusting meat packing and
pushed for food regulations. Ida Tarbell
is a muckreaker who investigated
Standard Oil and exposed their probably
illegal monopoly tactics. And finally,
Jacob Reese is a muckreaker who made the
book How the Other Half Lives, where the
book is packed full of photos and
reports exposing the horrid tenement
housing conditions. Moving on, let's go
over a different section of the
progressive movement, the political
side. Here we'll look at two people,
Theodore Roosevelt and Woodro Wilson.
Roosevelt argued for a quote square deal
where he pleaded to reign in
corporations, protect consumers, and
conserve natural resources. Wilson
argued for a quote new freedom by
restoring economic opportunity by
breaking up monopolies, lowering
tariffs, and reforming the banking
system. Notice how both of these ideals
are trying to regulate and reform most
of what the guilded age stood for. That
being said, there would also be a
movement of women's rights. We already
talked about the roots of this back in
unit 4 with the Senica Falls Convention.
Though later I did forget to mention
Susan Banthony, so apologies about that.
But now you have activists like Carrie
Chapman Cat and Alice Paul along with a
lot of women rallying behind the
movement. This women's movement will
continue to grow and will eventually
contribute a lot to two amendments later
on. Now let's move over to
African-American rights. Many
progressives were split or simply
ignored segregation as a whole. As for
people advocating for black rights, you
have Booker T. Washington, whom we
talked about earlier, and a new one for
you, webd boys, who simply demanded full
civil rights. Finally, the last two
progressive movements were immigration
and the environment. Immigration exposed
a split down the middle. Some
progressives pushed restrictions, while
others focused on supporting immigrants
and cities. Environmental reform
followed a similar pattern, dividing
into preservationists, who wanted to
protect nature for its own sake, and
conservationists, who emphasized
responsible long-term resource
management. Despite their differences,
both supported the creation of national
parks. Welcome to the A push version of
World War I. If you wonder why I have to
preface that by saying a push version,
it's because this war is technically
mostly an aspect of European history. I
mean, the war started in Europe. It
mostly happened in Europe and it ended
in Europe. So, from a US history
perspective, I would personally love to
go in and explain every tiny little
battle and complexity of this war, but I
can't. All I'm going to do here is give
you a little bit of context and explain
the US side of things. So, basically, by
1914, all these European powers had a
bunch of weapons. They were all
entangled in a bunch of alliances. And
most of all, they were all pretty full
of themselves. After some dude got
assassinated, one country declared war
on another country, which would cause a
big domino reaction because of the
alliances we talked about earlier, which
is why my favorite historical newspaper
has got to be this amazing one from The
Onion. So anyway, this war happens for a
while and by 1916, the war stalemates
into two big battles of trench warfare
at Verdun and the S. But if you're
wondering what the US is doing,
basically nothing is the answer. The US
wanted to maintain neutrality during
this war. However, it still sent ships
full of supplies to its allies. But then
you see two big things happen. First is
Germany's unrestricted submarine warfare
kept sinking ships with Americans on
them. The most famous of this was the
sinking of the Lucatania. Then by 1917
after the sinking started up again,
America got one more push to enter the
war. The Zimmerman telegram. This was an
encrypted message to Mexico from Germany
intercepted by Britain. It basically
tried to get Mexico to declare war on
the US if the US entered the war. So
this plus the constant sinking of
civilian ships caused America to enter
the war in April of 1917. Now I want you
to understand the American soldiers sent
to Europe known as the American
Expeditionary Forces played a relatively
limited role in combat. That being said,
this combined with constant American
supplies allowed the war to tip in favor
of the Allies and eventually Germany
would lose. This war would end with the
Treaty of Versailles and this will
easily be probably one of the most
biggest controversies in world history.
This treaty will basically force all
blame of the war on Germany and cause
them to pay an insane amount of
reparations. The US president at the
time, Woodro Wilson, also wanted to
create a League of Nations to try and
ally to make sure a war like this can
never happen again. However, Wilson will
fail to bring a Republican to the
discussion, which will cause him to lose
Republican support in Congress. And
ironically, despite him coming up with
the idea, Congress will choose for the
US not to join the League of Nations.
And just for numbers sakes here, about
20 million people died in World War I.
And for reference, only about a 100,000
will be from the US. So last video we
talked about World War I in Europe.
However, this is US history. So why
don't we now go back to America and take
a look at what it's like during and
after the war. Here's a good rule to go
by for both world wars and American
history. America is going to become kind
of unstable. I mean, we already know
lots of America is racist. I mean, Jim
Crow laws still exist and are still
being enforced quite a lot. But now
there are genuine threats in Europe that
America declares as enemies when they
enter the war. And so during and after
the war, many Americans will become more
willing to limit civil liberties,
especially freedom of speech because of
anxiety about disloyalty, radical
political ideas, and labor unrest. Good
examples here are the Espionage and
Sedation Acts, which were acts that
criminalized anti-war speech, and the
use of quote disloyal language. You also
have the American Protective League or
the APL, who literally volunteered to
report suspicious people. And after the
Russian Revolution started in 1917, a
period in American history known as the
first Red Scare happened where there was
a big fear that communists, anarchists,
and other radicals were threatening the
United States. Now, let's transition and
talk about immigration. Because before
World War I, immigration from Europe
reached very high levels. After the war,
nivism, which was the belief that the
interests of native born Americans
should be protected against immigrants,
increased. This is where you now see
quotas being implemented like the
emergency quota act and the 1924
immigration act which would both place
numerical limits on immigration by
creating quotas based on national
origin. A quick note that because of
increased wartime production there was a
big movement of people from small towns
into big industrial cities for factory
work. Now this factory work will mostly
be in the north and a whole bunch of
African-Americans still live down south
where they are being forced to adhere to
Jim Crow laws and have basically no
economic opportunities. So now when word
gets out that the north has lots of
high-paying factory jobs available,
something known as the great migration
happens where a bunch of
African-Americans will move out of the
south to the north. Now this would
create new black communities. But I do
want to teach something that actually is
roar taught in American history. That is
something known as the red summer of
1919. This is an effect of the great
migration where there will be a lot of
white mobs attacking black communities
in dozens of US cities and towns. The
roaring 20s. [music] What a time to be
alive. Oops. Sorry, but that's actually
supposed to be next topic. Lots of
people like studying the 1920s in
American history because of how much
cool culture there was, which is why we
refer to it as the roaring 20s. Right
now, we're going to talk about what
facilitated and caused this quote
roaring 20s. Basically, this comes down
to two things. New technology and mass
media. Let's first talk about the
technology. And for this, we will look
at two people. Let's start with Henry
Ford. Ford here popularized something
very revolutionary known as assembly
lines. Meaning he broke down production
into simple repeated steps causing a
faster output which would then cause the
price of goods to go down. The second
part to this is something called
scientific management where you
prioritize efficiency over everything
else. The man attributed to this is a
man named Frederick Taylor. Oh, and
before we move on, the biggest
innovation in this time period and
arguably in the entirety of world
history will be the automobile. It's
truly indescribable how much the
automobile changes everything. Commuting
changes, roads will be built, gas
stations and motel are made and it would
cause an unforeseen level of suburban
growth. But now let's go over to our
second thing and talk about the media.
Because other than the automobile, you
have two more things that boomed in this
time period. Cinema and the radio. With
cinema, we are obviously talking about
the growth of Hollywood and movies,
which would give Americans shared
celebrities, fashion, slang, and even
values. The more impactful one here
though is probably radios because now
instead of waiting for a newspaper,
people can have live broadcasts, news,
music, sports, advertising. And the big
importance here is that people across
the country are all listening to the
same stuff. This created a consumer
economy, meaning people are buying
appliances, cars, and entertainment,
often through credit and installment
plans. This would also facilitate the
means of which cultures will spread
across America throughout the 20s,
especially regional ones, and make
something like the Roaring 20s possible.
Oh, the Roaring 20s. What a time to be
alive. So much culture define this era
of American history. So, why don't we
walk down this 1920s street and explore
some cultural phenomena. The first stop
on this street is the lovely bar, which
we call a speak easy, because obviously
alcohol is illegal in this time period
after the 18th amendment. Look at those
lovely flappers dancing on stage. While
behind them, a jazz band fills the room
with fast-paced rhythms that symbolize a
break from tradition and the rise of a
new American sound. The bar is packed
with people from different backgrounds,
a rare sight for the time, all gathered
in defiance of one thing, prohibition.
But the bar isn't the only thing we see.
Our next stop is Harlem, New York, where
the great migration has caused a surge
of African-American culture known as the
Harlem Renaissance. In the building down
the street, I think I see two people,
Zoranil Hursten and Langston Hughes, who
are proving that black people can write
great literature. But coming up closer,
I see two great artists of Bessie Smith
and Lily Armstrong, creating and
performing lovely jazz to all that can
behold it. Our last stop here is the
local library where women finally gain
new visibility in society with their new
right to vote in women's suffrage
movement. And I think I even catch a
sight of Alice Paul in the corner
helping out. Man, this era of American
history is truly something special. All
right, that's enough of that. Yes, this
era looks incredible on the surface.
However, it's kind of hard to explain,
but it's all kind of empty and trashy
below the surface. Prohibition causes
widespread crime and the growth of civil
unrest on top of numerical quotas.
Immigrants get treated even worse with
these two Supreme Court decisions. And
though this era is defined by vast
amounts of money everywhere, you got to
remember what comes literally right
after this era. The 1920s is all surface
level. And the reason it will collapse
so quickly when the depression hits is
because everything is built on beliefs
and borrowed money. The whole era seems
cute and incredible on the surface, but
truly everything you see is hanging on a
tight thread. So before we end this
topic, I think it's only right since we
talked about all the good. Let's talk
about the famous bad things that
happened in the 20s. The Scopes monkey
trial upheld a Tennessee law banning the
teaching of evolution. In Buck versus
Bell, the Supreme Court ruled that it
was okay to remove some people's ability
to have children, known as
sterilization. And finally, Nicolasako
and Bartala Benzetti had a very unfair
murder trial, likely because of their
Italian heritage, and they got sentenced
to death and executed despite their
likely innocence. On the surface, the
1920s was great. It truly was. I mean,
do you remember back to units 1 and two
of this course where we talked about
America being founded on people living
in the rural countryside? Now, we have
gone so far with so many big
corporations that in the 20s it will be
the first time in American history where
there's more people living in big urban
cities than in the rural countryside.
So, if the 20s are so glamorous, how
exactly can something like the Great
Depression even happen? Here's your
answer with four reasons. The first is
simply overprouction because the
American economy was so industrial that
during the 20s it produced more goods
than people could buy. The second is
debt because pretty much all consumers
and businesses were deeply in debt. The
reason for that is that all the lavish
things bought by these people in the 20s
were purchased through things like
credit and not actual real paper money.
The third one here though is a bank/
Federal Reserve failure because banks
were giving out risky loans, had little
oversight, and collapsed when people
rushed to withdraw their money and the
Federal Reserve didn't step in to help.
And finally, the fourth reason was the
economy around the world was not that
great. European economies depended on US
loans after World War I. So when US
banks collapsed, loans were recalled.
And with all these four causes in play,
it's like a room full of gas that
requires one spark for the whole room to
go boom. And that spark will be when the
stock market crashes in 1929. Pretty
quickly, the Great Depression will be
devastating. Millions will lose their
jobs, homes, and savings. The
unemployment rate will shoot up to a
staggering 25%. Millions who couldn't
afford food lined up in historically
long bread lines where there was never
enough food to go around. And people who
lost their homes built makeshift
shelters out of scrap wood and cardboard
which would make shanty towns known as
quote Hoovervilles. Families would
migrate all over the place to search for
work and children would often go without
school. As for the initial federal
response, it will be quite weak and be
based on voluntary cooperation between
businesses and government. Pretty
quickly when this doesn't work, America
will redefine itself in the ideas of
modern American liberalism. This will
call for the regulation of markets,
social insurance, and most importantly,
responsibility in the hands of
government for economic well-being. That
means bye-bye lzair. It was nice knowing
you. So, there's this big misconception
through the understanding of US history
that the Great Depression happens and
right afterwards, the New Deal comes
along and ends the Great Depression. To
put it bluntly, no, the New Deal does
not end the Great Depression. The
technical end comes with the
mobilization for World War II. I'd say
the new deal itself is more of something
that reshaped the US government. So,
let's recap here. Herbert Hoover is
president, the depression starts, and
poor old Lad Hoover over here doesn't
really know what to do and is criticized
heavily for it. So, when Franklin
Delanor Roosevelt or FDR came along as
the Democratic nominee in the 1932
election, it's a pretty simple and easy
victory for him. Fairly quickly, FDR
will implement his New Deal plan. And
this is quite complex, but to give it a
sentence definition, FDR's New Deal will
use aggressive government intervention
to stabilize the economy, put people
back to work, and prevent another
depression from happening again. The
method that will be used here is
something we like to call the three Rs:
relief, recovery, and reform. Very
quickly, you'll start seeing programs.
Let's go through a few of them. The
Civilian Conservation Corpse employed
young men in environmental and
infrastructure projects. There were lots
of public works/infrastructure programs
that built roads, parks, dams, schools,
and public buildings, and separate
programs existed for Native Americans,
Puerto Rico, and African-Ameans. If you
can't tell, all of these existed so
there would be more jobs for people to
get. But what I want you to notice here
is the big contradiction of what we
established back in unit 6. Do you
remember when America functioned on a
hands-off approach and letting the
economy do its own thing? Now, with this
New Deal, it will easily be up to this
point in history, the biggest government
intervention in its own economy that
America has ever had. And since this New
Deal changed American policy so much,
there was quite a lot of debates on both
sides of Roosevelt. Radicals, unions,
and populist movements such as Hugh Long
and Father Charles Coughlin will push
Roosevelt to intervene as much as
possible with government efforts. But on
the other side, conservatives in
Congress and the Supreme Court sought to
limit the New Deal's overall scope. An
example of this is the Supreme Court
case Shreker Poultry Corp. versus the
United States, which struck down parts
of the National Industry Recovery Act.
And finally, the last thing about the
New Deal is the institutions it created
that still exists to this day. The
GlassSteagall Act separated commercial
banking from investment banking, and the
Social Security Act gave old age
pensions, unemployment insurance, and
aid for the disabled. If you can't tell,
everything about this new deal will
cause workingclass communities to
identify more with the Democratic Party.
We are currently positioned squarely in
the inter war period in American
history. So here's a good question to
ask after World War I. Should America
lead globally or stay out of foreign
conflicts? If you want to know the
answer to this question, it is mostly to
stay out of everything, meaning to be
isolationists. However, there were quite
a few things that happened that went
against this ideology. The first of this
is two things. The DA plan was made
because Germany could not pay for its
reparations and Europe was struggling as
a result. So the plan was to loan
Germany money which after Germany paid
their reparations allowed Britain and
France to pay off their US war debts.
Then later the Kellogg brand pact was
passed in which most countries pledged
to not solve world problems with war.
And if you can't tell both of these
things did not work. The DAW plan failed
because of the Great Depression and the
Kellogg Brand Pact failed because there
was no way it could be enforced. It's
also important to note that the US
continued intervention and continued
presence in Latin America and the
Caribbean such as in Haiti and
Nicaragua. But now we see something else
rise in Europe and that is a very famous
mustache man with an ideology of fascism
growing very strong. The US sensed war
might come and passed a series of
neutrality acts which didn't really
work. And over in Europe, our good
friend Hitler is conquering land and the
horrible method of appeasement isn't
alleviating it. Once FDR realizes these
access powers are dangerous, he slowly
starts moving away from isolationism.
And then out of nowhere, bam, the naval
base Pearl Harbor is bombed by the Axis
power Japan and America officially
enters World War II. So the US is now
officially in World War II. But to put
it bluntly, US entry into World War II
required total economic mobilization.
That means all the work needed to make
cars, tanks, and weapons will cause so
much jobs, which effectively will end
the Great Depression. And here's another
part to this. All the men are getting
shipped off to war. That means the
people that will step up to do this
factory work will mostly be women. That
means during the war, women had many new
gains as they took over male-dominated
jobs. However, it should be noted many
women were pushed out of the jobs after
the war when men returned. But women
aren't the only one that get
opportunities. African-Ameans do as
well. They will also work in factories.
However, they will face their own share
of racism. But the other people that get
opportunities here are immigrants and
migrants. There will be so much
migration to big cities that places like
Los Angeles, Oakland, Seattle, and
Detroit will grow like crazy. The
specific immigrants I want to mention
here are Mexican ones. Because you start
seeing a vast amount of Mexican
immigrants that entered the US during
the war under the Breretta program,
which allowed Mexican laborers to
temporarily work in US agriculture and
railroad jobs. I'm sure you can guess,
but the response you'll see to this is
racism. An example of that is the Zoot
Sweet riots where Mexicans and Filipinos
were attacked in LA over a series of
days. And the last thing I want to say
is a lot of people like to say FDR was
one of the greatest presidents. I won't
really say anything on the matter, but
here is something that doesn't look too
good on his part. During World War II,
fear and racism led FDR to issue an
executive order which would force around
120,000 Japanese Americans into
internment camps. And these camps were
not good in the slightest. It's time to
talk about World War II. This war will
be like no other in history. The US will
directly fight Japan in the Pacific
theater, and the Allied powers will
fight Germany in Europe. After Pearl
Harbor in Congress's Declaration of War,
Americans will view this war as a fight
for the survival of freedom and
democracy against fascist and
militaristic ideologies. And this view
on the war isn't too far off from the
truth. Because later in the war, it was
realized the horrible things the Axis
powers were up to. In Germany,
minorities with a special emphasis on
Jewish citizens will be forced into
horrible concentration death camps where
it is said that over 6 million Jewish
will die. Over in Japan, their invasion
of China will showcase horrific
tragedies such as the rape of Nank King,
where Chinese civilians in disarmed
soldiers were mass murdered, raped, and
eluded. Fascism posed such a threat that
this war was about more than just
victory or defeat. Like in World War I,
the Allies had to win or the world would
be fundamentally changed. America
quickly recognized this leading to full
national mobilization. Industries surged
and women and minorities joined the war
effort through groups like the Women's
Army Auxiliary Corpse and Anisai units
of Japanese American soldiers. So let's
go over to the war now. We'll first talk
about the European theater. Basically by
1944, Germany had conquered France and
part of the Soviet Union. On the eastern
side, the winter allowed the Soviets to
regroup and push back against Germany
with probably the most important turning
point battle in world history being the
battle of Stalenrad. On the western
side, the Allies needed to push back
against Germany. So on June 6th, 1944, a
combination of American, British, and
Canadian forces stormed the northern
beaches of France, which was known as
D-Day. This was a huge success, and the
Allied forces will continue pushing on
the west while the Soviets will push on
the east, and eventually Hitler will be
defeated. Now, let's head over to the
Pacific theater. The turning point
battle here is when America will destroy
a bunch of Japanese aircraft carriers,
and that will happen at the Battle of
Midway. After Midway, America will start
taking back islands that Japan had
conquered during the war. However, this
will reveal a grim reality. Japanese
soldiers fought with extreme brutality,
and their code of honor compelled them
to fight to the death, making the island
hopping campaign extremely brutal and
costly. By the end of the war, America
had developed the atomic bomb thanks to
the Manhattan Project. This bomb would
kill so many people, but it could force
the fierce Japanese to surrender. And
with so many American soldiers dying in
this island hopping, America would be
forced to make a difficult choice. And I
think Oppenheimer will put it best.
>> Now I am become death, the destroyer of
worlds.
>> Two a bombs will be dropped. Hundreds of
thousands of innocent people will die.
Japan will surrender. And it will be one
of the biggest moral debates for the
rest of history. World War II was just
simply devastating. Around 80 million
people will die over the course of this
six-year long war. However, the thing
about this war from a US history
perspective is that this war was pretty
much fought everywhere except the US.
After the war, Europe and Asia will be
devastated in both casualties and land.
I mean, just look at these images on the
screen. So, now the US will have a
massive military, industrial capacity,
and mostly untouched land. Meaning
finally the United States will emerge as
the most powerful country in the world
upon the conclusion of this war. The
Yalta and Potam conferences will happen
near the end of the war. The key
outcomes you should know are that
Germany will be divided into occupation
zones. Japan will be occupied and
rebuilt under US supervision. War crime
trials will be held against Nazi leaders
in borders/governments across Europe and
Asia will be reorganized. The other
consequence of this war is the creation
of the United Nations or UN. This will
allow countries to negotiate, prevent
wars, and promote cooperation. But very
quickly, you'll see the Soviet Union
occupied most of Eastern Europe, enforce
a communist ideology, which will lead to
a different kind of war that we refer to
as being very cold. But I think we'll
cover that next unit.
So, World War II is now over. In the end
of this war, we'll see the rise of two
major global superpowers, the Soviet
Union and the United States. The thing
is, these two superpowers were allies
during World War II. And pretty much
immediately after the war, their
alliance collapses. The reason for this
is pretty simple. These two countries
ideologies are completely different.
Over in the US, we have democracy,
capitalism in free markets. However,
going over to the Soviet Union, we now
have a system known as authoritarian
communism, which means the state
controls literally everything. So, you
might think that these two countries are
going to go to war. But the world just
went through a horribly devastating war,
and now things like nuclear weapons
exist. If another war were to happen,
it's not unreasonable to say that the
world could quite literally come to an
end. So, the thing that emerges, the
Cold War, isn't a normal war at all. It
will be a 45- year long series of
smaller conflicts and tensions that over
time add up to one massive quote cold
war. So, from 1945 to 1980, one thing
will remain constant, containment.
Simply meaning that the US's goal is to
stop communism from spreading. This idea
comes from George Kennan's long telegram
where he argues that the Soviet Union
will expand unless firmly contained. So
let's give some examples of this
containment. First is economic aid. The
Truman doctrine will be made declaring
the US will give money to Greece and
Turkey to stop communist influence. Also
the Marshall Plan will be enacted to
send billions of dollars to rebuild
Western Europe after the war. But the
second thing here is military alliances.
Western democracies will ally under the
North Atlantic Treaty Organization or
NATO. And later the Soviet Union will
respond and create the Warsaw Pact for
all of its countries. And now notice
that with these new organizations, the
world is essentially split in half.
Finally, the last thing here will be
military conflicts. This is where we see
proxy wars like the Korean War. And
looking at this, basically North Korea
is communist and wants to invade the
democratic South Korea. The US will ally
with the South, the communist China will
ally with the North and the war happens.
And after 3 years, it will end in a
draw. Cool. Then the Cuban missile
crisis will have the Soviets place
nuclear missiles in Cuba. The US
blockades Cuba. The world nearly ends.
But all is good after some negotiation.
But by the 1970s, this Cold War had
really gone on for long enough. Vietnam
is something that we'll cover later in
this unit. Let's just say that the US
was not having a great time in Vietnam.
Under Nixon, various treaties and open
communications between the US and China/
the Soviet Union will happen. And the
key method of the cold war will now turn
to something called deont, meaning to
ease tensions. There are also so many
other parts to this cold war that I do
not have time to go over. Just
understand that the US used a lot of
different strategies over the years to
manage the Soviet threat on the cold
war. It isn't exactly limited to
conflicts with the Soviet Union. I mean,
yes, that is the definition on paper,
but the Cold War will also cause a lot
of things to happen specifically in
America. Specifically for this video, I
want to talk to you about the Red Scare.
But before that, let's head over to
postworld war II Europe. Despite the
US's efforts to contain communism, in
1949, the Soviet Union gets an atomic
bomb. And also in 1949, China will
become communist. And right after that,
in 1950, the Korean War starts. With all
this happening so quickly, fear began to
grow that communism might reach the
United States. And that fear will cause
an era known as the second big red scare
where anti-communist paranoia in America
will lead to blacklisting, ruined
reputations, and widespread
intimidation. And the big person I want
to mention here is a senator named
Joseph McCarthy. And for all you Gen Z
kids, this man is the perfect definition
of a rage baiter. He basically claimed
communists were everywhere in the
government, but often had little to no
evidence to back it up. And I think this
perfectly encapsulates this era because
now we see accusations of communism
without any proof, careers being
destroyed left and right as a result and
all of it really just leading to a
massive public fear. And this will also
lead to serious limits on civil
liberties, especially freedom of speech.
Now, let's give some examples of things
that happened in the Red Scare. Truman's
executive order 9835, also known as the
Loyalty Order, investigated government
employees for quote disloyalty and led
to thousands losing their jobs. The
House on American Activities Committee
investigated suspected communists with a
special focus on Hollywood where
specifically in Hollywood 10 writers,
directors, and screenwriters were cited
and blacklisted from the industry. And
finally, there were actual real
espionage cases such as Alger, but the
more dramatic one here was probably the
Rosenbergs where after these two were
convicted of selling secrets to the
Soviet Union, they were executed by
electric chair. But moving on, by the
end of the 50s, push back against
McCarthyism, such as criticism by
Margaret Chase Smith, will inevitably
cause paranoia to die down, and the
whole red scare by the end of the 50s
will essentially dissipate. But just
remember, even though people argued
about methods, both political parties in
this era agree that communism must be
stopped. So, World War II is over. And
looking at America from an economic
standpoint, after World War II, America
goes through massive economic growth.
And there is a lot of reasons for this.
Large corporations expand rapidly,
meaning more goods are produced and more
of a consumer economy develops. Also of
note is that the federal government
played a major role in boosting the
economy. Let's go through a few very
important things. The GI Bill provided
all these millions of World War II
veterans with money for college,
housing, and business loans. And the
Interstate Highway Act launched a
massive road building project, which is
the reason there are all of these
highways around the country. So with the
economy being strong, people wanted more
babies. And that's where we see a
massive spike in the birth rate post
World War II, known as the baby boom.
And more people in the world means more
of a demand for houses and goods, which
is where we see all of these
technologies on the screen being
manufactured in this time period, which
contributed more to the greater economic
boom. So now we see a couple of things.
The country's economy is very strong.
Goods are being bought and sold at high
levels. And now there are roads all over
the place. So the result of this will be
a lot of migration. Specifically,
millions of middle-class Americans moved
from big cities to suburbs. The reason
for this is pretty simple. Roads make
transportation way faster. There is
affordable housing with FHA loans in the
GI Bill. And also lots of houses are
being built. And the thing I want to
reference here is mass-produced
neighborhoods full of houses that look
the exact same, which was very common in
this time period known as a levy town. A
good area where people migrated to was
the Sunb Belt. All because of the
recently invented air conditioning,
which made living in this hot region
more plausible. However, despite all of
the economic improvements, you have to
understand that you had to be a very
specific skin color to get access to
these improvements. That's right.
Governmentbacked housing policies often
excluded minorities. This was known as
redlining, by the way. And this would
mean suburban growth was racially
unequal. Take a look at this man. He
looks pretty cool. But then take a look
at the guy next to him. It's the same
dang person. Yeah, that's right. This is
basically the 1950s in American history.
The reason I say that is because during
the ' 50s, people across the country
started living very similar lives,
meaning American culture became
increasingly homogeneous. Now, it's
pretty easy to see why this is the case.
The television becomes massive and every
American is watching them. And to add to
that, TV shows promote a nuclear family,
meaning where the husband works and the
wife stays at home. Shows also showed
suburban life and traditional gender
roles. So now everyone is watching and
being influenced by the same things. But
it's not just that. The economic boom of
the ' 50s also means everyone is buying
the same stuff such as cars, appliances,
and again TVs. And now with Americans
living in the suburbs, again, remember
this is what an American neighborhood
looks like. It's all the same. So when
you look at the 50s in American history
from a cultural standpoint, the big
label you can truly give it is calling
it conformist. meaning people are
following the same norms, expectations,
and lifestyles. Now, though what I said
is all true, it wasn't technically all
the same. There is some push back
against conformity in this time period.
Let's go through some examples. The beat
movement happened where writers and
poets rejected consumerism and
traditional values. Rock and roll surged
with artists like Chuck Barry and Elvis
Presley. I mean, listen to this song by
Elvis.
Sorry, that's all I can play so I don't
get copyrighted. The last two things
here are intellectual criticism of
aspects of American culture and also
there were early movements in the LGBTQ
plus movement with an example being the
Matteen society which were one of the
earliest most influential US gay rights
organizations. Hello there. To start
this video, I want to flash back to my
final unit 5 video where I said this.
Reconstruction was the US's first
attempt at civil rights and it failed
miserably. But the 14th and 15th
amendments didn't go away. They became
the legal foundation for the civil
rights movement a 100red years later. So
yeah, it's finally a hundred years later
and it's time to talk about the civil
rights movement. So let's look at a
typical group of black Americans in the
1950s. You might be surprised to know
this, but at this time blacks were
legally forced to go to separate
schools, use different bathrooms and
water fountains, sit in the back of
buses, and were often blocked from
voting, certain jobs, and even
neighborhoods, all because of the color
of their skin. So now a lot of black
soldiers fought for freedom in World War
II and then they come back to legally
sanctioned segregation at home. This was
not sustainable anymore. So the big
African-American rights organization,
the NAACP, went for a very specific
strategy to combat segregation. And that
strategy was challenging segregation in
courts with a big lawyer in this regard
being Thood Marshall. And this will all
lead to our three branches of government
acting albeit at different times. In the
executive branch, Truman will
desegregate the military. In the
judicial, the very important Brown
versus Board of Education case happens,
which declared school segregation as
unconstitutional, meaning it overturned
Py. Ferguson's separate but equal
doctrine. And finally, in the
legislative branch, the Civil Rights Act
of 1957 was passed. It was pretty weak
and didn't really do much, but it is
symbolic as the first civil rights law
since reconstruction. So now we see the
Civil Rights Movement expand. For
example, courts became key battlegrounds
for arguing civil rights. And obviously,
we have our two main civil rights
organizations. And who can forget the
lady who refused to give up her seat on
a Montgomery bus. That's right. Rosa
Park caught at Culvin. Oh, and I guess
Rosa Parks also did it, too. After Rosa
Parks got arrested for not giving up her
bus seat to a white man, the black
community in Montgomery responded by
boycotting the entire bus system,
causing it to lose a lot of money. With
a key figure growing here being Martin
Luther King Jr., This would lead to bus
segregation being ruled unconstitutional
in Browder v. Gale. And finally, in
Little Rock, Arkansas, nine black
students enrolled at a previously
all-white high school. The governor of
Arkansas didn't like this and tried to
block these students from entering
school by sending in the National Guard
to block them. In violent racism erupted
as crowds protested their entry. So,
despite Brown v. Board ruling
segregation illegal, Arkansas didn't
care. So, President Dwight D. Eisenhower
had to act. So, what he did was take
control of the National Guard away from
the governor of Arkansas and even sent
his own troops to ensure the students
could enter the school safely. It's been
a second since we've talked about it.
So, let's head on over back to the Cold
War. Last time we talked a lot about the
Cold War in Europe and also in the US,
but now the Cold War will expand to all
over the world. Let's first head over to
Latin America. And really quickly, the
key point I want to make here before I
talk about anything is that the US will
support any government that is
anti-communist, even if it's not
democratic. So over in Guatemala, the US
sees a leader who makes controversial,
potentially communist influence, land
reform. So the CIA helps overthrow him.
Over in Chile, a socialist democracy is
made with another democratically elected
guy. And so the US supported his coup
d'eta. But it's not all sunshine and
rainbows. Cuba was a country directly
aligned with the Soviet Union. So the US
decides to launch an invasion known as
the Bay of Pigs. And through a lot of
reasons, it completely fails. But now
moving over to Africa and the Middle
East, most of these newly formed
countries tried to stay out of the Cold
War, meaning they were quote
non-aligned. However, the US still
intervened a bit. The US will help
overthrow a leader in Iran. Help
negotiate peace between Egypt and
Israel. And in Angola, there was a proxy
war between the USSR and the US.
Honestly, it's a dang chess match. That
is the best way I can describe the Cold
War. But unlike a chess match, there
were actual consequences. And that was
the nuclear threat of a fear of
annihilation. That is where a concept of
MAD is declared, which means mutually
assured destruction. Meaning, if one
side launches nukes, the other side is
going to do the same. Sure, this does
prevent war, but it will also lead to a
massive arms buildup and debates around
America will spark up about spending in
the military. This will even lead to
Eisenhower warning about the quote
militaryindustrial complex where he
warned that government plus military
plus corporations held way too much
power in the United States. So, this
cold war is intense in many ways, but it
is not over by a long shot. And it's
time to talk about one of its biggest
conflicts, which was the Vietnam War.
So, let's look at a map of Southeast
Asia. After defeating France, Vietnam
split into the communist North under Ho
Chi Min and the non-communist South
Vietnam. And almost immediately, the two
sides go to war. The US's thinking here
will be the domino theory, which was the
belief that if Vietnam fell to
communism, other Southeast Asian
countries would follow. So, the US
essentially just wanted to contain
communism spread. So, it starts off
pretty simple. The US will start by
sending money and advisers. But then the
Gulf of Tonkan incident happens where
two US boats are attacked by North
Vietnam. Now, in retrospect, this
incident was very exaggerated and parts
of it were likely made up, but it didn't
really matter because it caused the
president at the time, Lyndon B.
Johnson, to use the incident to justify
full military involvement in Vietnam by
the US. And so, the US will officially
enter Vietnam. It will implement a full
military draft and send hundreds of
thousands of untrained young boys to
fight. And it will quickly become a
full-on war. Once the US is fully
involved in Vietnam, the war quickly
becomes a nightmare because it isn't a
traditional fight. Communist soldiers
who supported the North but fought in
the South were called the Vietkong and
they do not operate like regular
soldiers. Instead, they move within
South Vietnam using the Ho Chi Min Trail
for supplies. They blend in with
civilians and rely on ambushes, booby
traps, and tunnel systems. This makes it
incredibly difficult for millions of US
soldiers to tell who the enemy is. So
then you see a few things happen. The
Ted offensive happens in Vietnam where
North Vietnamese soldiers launch a
massive series of surprise attacks on
the South and then the Pentagon papers
get released showing that US leaders had
been secretly expanding and
misrepresenting the war while lying to
the public saying that things were under
control. And finally the my lie massacre
happens where US soldiers killed
hundreds of unarmed Vietnamese
civilians. All of these combined
together cause the US public to most
openly despise this war. The result here
is college protests, widespread draft
resistance, and cultural divide. This
will lead to the War Powers Act, which
basically said that the president can't
just drag the US into war without
Congress. And finally, when Nixon
becomes president, he begins pulling US
soldiers out of Vietnam until finally in
1975, the US officially exits the war.
North Vietnam wins and Vietnam becomes
communist. How about that? For once in
history, the US actually loses. So back
over in America, even though the economy
was booming by the '60s, people start
realizing that not everyone is
benefiting. A book that acted as a very
good expose was The Other America by
Michael Harrington. Basically, this book
revealed that there was a hidden poverty
in America, revealing the struggles of
millions of poor Americans. And then on
top of this, because of the result of
World War II and the economic boom of
the '50s, by the 1960s, American
citizens have almost full confidence in
its own liberal government and thinks
the government can solve social issues.
This will all lead President Lyndon B.
Johnson to enact his Great Society,
which was an expansion of the New Deal
focused on social issues rather than
just the economy, aiming to end poverty,
reduce racial inequality, improve
education, and expand healthcare. Let's
go over the things the Great Society
created. Programs focusing on poverty
will be implemented, such as the Job
Corpse for job training, Head Start for
Early Childhood Education, and the Food
Stamp Act for food assistance. Healthc
care programs will also be implemented,
such as Medicare for the elderly and
Medicaid for the poor. It's also
important to note that this plan for a
great society often worked alongside the
ongoing civil rights movement at the
time. The other part to this though is
immigration and we see this with the
immigration act of 1965 where finally
quotas are removed meaning we see a lot
more immigration from Latin America and
Asia which permanently changed US
demographics. So you might be asking now
was this great society a good success or
bad overall? Well, it obviously did have
successes that we still see in our
society to this day. But I want you to
understand something. Remember the
guilded age where America had a very
small government and didn't intervene in
its economy at all. Remember the whole
azair thing? Now we have gone through
the New Deal, World War II, and now the
Great Society. So the result is the US
government is as big as it has ever been
and it is intervening as much in its own
economy as it ever has. Conservatives on
the right will argue that the government
is way too big now and later past the
70s into the 80s. Things like Vietnam
and a lot of government spending will
cause mass inflation and unemployment
leading to a growing distrust in
government and a resulting age of
conservatism. But I get ahead of myself.
It's time to talk about the official
African-American civil rights movement.
We already talked about the roots of
this with Rosa Parks, the bus boycott,
and the Little Rock N, but pretty
quickly the movement expands even
bigger. So here is what you need to
know. During the early part of the civil
rights movement in the 60s, the overall
goal was nonviolent protest because
violence would undermine the goal of the
movement. The leader of this movement
will be a man named Martin Luther King
Jr. So why don't we go through some
examples of this movement. Sitins were
protests where black activists sat at
segregated lunch counters refusing to
leave until served. Freedom rides
happened where people of many races sat
in white only sections of buses
throughout the south to challenge
segregation. And finally, there were a
lot of marches in big cities. For
example, in the March on Washington,
Martin Luther King Jr. went up on a
stage and gave his I have a dream speech
where he pleaded to thousands of people
about his dreams of a world without
blatant segregation. And it would easily
become one of the most famous speeches
in world history. And by this point, the
non-violent movement had gotten so big
that it finally pushed real federal
action. The 1964 Civil Rights Act is
passed, [music] which completely ends
segregation and bans discrimination. The
Voting Rights Act is also passed which
protected black voting rights and also
the other two branches of government do
a few things as well. Here is the issue
though because even if the federal
government passed all these laws,
poverty still exists, racism still
exists and urban violence actually
steadily rises and this is where the
civil rights movement will essentially
split in half. On one side, you have the
Martin Luther King inspired non-violent
protests, but now on the other side, you
have a growing group of people
advocating for more aggressive measures
like self-defense, black pride, and
economic independence. A leader to
reference here is Malcolm X. This second
movement based on black power gets
really popular and leads to groups like
the Black Panthers, who again advocate
for more aggressive measures. It's also
important to note that these two very
important leaders will get assassinated,
which definitely does not help the
non-violent side of things. So, there is
an obvious split here. And this will
mean by the midpoint of the 60s, the
civil rights movement is not necessarily
one thing anymore. It is a movement
divided behind different methods full of
a lot of ongoing struggles. So, this
African-American civil rights movement
has gotten really big by the '60s. So,
the big idea here is all these other
groups of minorities are seeing the
success of this big movement and are
getting inspired to do something similar
with their group. We have five groups to
go over in this video, so let's get into
it. Latinos will start the Chico
Movement. Rural leaders like Caesar
Chavez will form the United Farm Workers
to fight low wages and poor working
conditions. An example of things they
did were nonviolent things such as a
national consumer boycott of California
Table Grapes. This would lead to union
contracts, better wages, and safer
working conditions. Moving on, though,
American Indians formed their own
movement as well. The goal here was to
reclaim their own rights and protest
government treatment. The two big things
that happened here were that Native
American groups would forcibly occupy
the prison Alcatres and the town of
Wounded Knee in an effort to protest the
federal government. But now, let's move
over to Asian-Americans. This one was
more focused on giving Asians their own
identity in America. And lots of what
you see here are college protests
against anti-Asian racism. Now let's
move over to feminism. If you remember
in the past we had our era of firstwave
feminism. Now we are in the technical
second wave where women are going to
advocate for full equal rights such as
equal pay, workplace equality and an
equal rights amendment. An organization
here popularized was the national
organization for women or now. And a
really important book made here was
Bessie Frerieden's The Feminine
Mystique, which exposed the lack of
fulfillment an American housewife truly
has. And finally, the LGBTQ plus
community had their own movement as well
to try and fight discrimination and
demand recognition. A key turning point
in this movement was the Stonewall
riots, which would eventually lead to a
later gay liberation movement. Let's go
over a few things right now. The Vietnam
War is causing millions of young men to
be drafted. The Pentagon Papers has
exposed the government lies and caused a
mass distrust. And the civil rights
movement is proving that protesting can
work to change the norm. And so the
result we see here is the youngsters of
society starting to question authority
and rebel. We already talked about
instances of this like college protests
and marches. But a very important event
I haven't mentioned is the Ken State
Massacre where a large group of students
at Ken State University were protesting
Vietnam. One thing led to another and
four people ended up being shot and
killed by the US National Guard in the
crowd. But moving on, now what we see is
a new variation of left in society
called the students for a democratic
society who believed the government
wasn't doing enough socially but was too
aggressive militarily. This group
criticized things like war, inequality,
and government power. And the final form
of this youth culture is the formation
of a counterculture social rebellion.
This is where you see the hippies of the
' 60s rejecting traditional jobs, gender
roles, and materialism. This will create
a more rebellious informal society. Here
is a good way to remember the hippie
movement. Peace, love, sex, and a whole
lot of grass, which is slaying for lots
and lots and lots of drugs. So, in this
time period, finally, it is realized by
American society that the environment
essentially exists. The reason behind
this is because a lot of bad environment
related things happen all at once. This
river, which I'm not going to pronounce
the name of, literally caught on fire.
This town was built upon a bunch of
toxic waste, causing a surge of diseases
such as cancer. And this power plant
almost completely melted down. And from
all of this, people start to realize
industrial growth just might be messing
up the environment. Oh, but it gets
worse. Of course, what I'm referring to
here is the energy crisis where
basically there was severe fuel
shortages in the Middle East the US
depended on causing prices at gas
stations to spike and for there to be
historically long gas station lines.
This will all finally cause some
environmental action. Let's go through
some examples. The Environmental
Protection Agency will be created. The
Clean Air Act will limit emissions and
the Endangered Species Act will protect
endangered animals/plants. As for
energy, the Department of Energy will be
created and the US will shift a focus
more on energy independence. The 1950s
and 1960s, there is a big word I want to
throw out there and say trust. Because
these two eras of American history saw
many people trust the American liberal
government. And now I want to put it
bluntly as we are in the 70s. The
optimism of the ' 50s and early 60s is
now gone. Vietnam is an utter failure
and causes people to distrust the
government. But then the truly infamous
Watergate scandal happens where
President Richard Nixon covers up a
burglary at the Democratic National
Committee headquarters, revealing
widespread illegal surveillance and
political sabotage leading to Nixon's
presidential resignation in 1974. And
not to mention the 1970s American
economy had high inflation and growing
unemployment, which is a very rare
economic phenomenon called stagflation.
When we get into Jimmy Carter's
presidency, it doesn't get much better.
The energy crisis moves into full
effect. A hostage crisis in Iran made
the government appear ineffective. And
now by this point, distrust in the
United States government by its own
citizens is at an all-time high. The
liberals in society have dominated the
political landscape for so long now
dating all the way back to the New Deal.
But now with this combination of things,
conservatives are going to rise through
the cracks. Conservatives will have an
ideology of thinking the government is
way too big. So they want less
regulation. a stronger military and a
push back to traditional values. Not to
mention you also see a rise of
evangelical Christianity which will
become more intertwined with politics
specifically intertwining with the
conservative side. This will lead to the
80s later where conservatism will take
over.
So in our last unit we've established
that by the 80s citizens of America have
lost confidence in the greater American
government for a variety of reasons. So
now coming back into this, people start
to think maybe the government is the
problem, not the solution. And that
right there is the opening for
conservatives. Enter Ronald Reagan. He
will argue that the government is too
big, taxes are too high, regulations
hurt businesses, welfare programs don't
actually fix poverty and that society
needs more quote traditional values. And
after Ronald Reagan gets elected, pretty
quickly an economic system called
regonomics is enacted. This is broken
into three parts. First, you have tax
cuts, meaning that people plus
businesses keep more money. The second
here is deregulation, meaning that there
will be fewer government rules on
industries. And finally, you have supply
side economics, where helping businesses
grow is supposed to help everyone,
meaning more jobs, more goods, and a
stronger economy overall. But anyway,
I'm sure you are wondering whether or
not this is a good or bad idea. Well,
it's not really my place to say. Rather,
what I will do here is objectively
explain what both political sides
thought of this, and you can decide
whether it's good or bad yourself.
Conservatives would argue that
regonomics would grow the economy, make
inflation go down, and allow businesses
to expand. But the liberals, on the
other hand, would argue regonomics
basically mostly benefited the rich and
would cause the wealth gap in the US
deficit to grow. And also something
important to note is that even though
Reagan wanted a smaller government,
programs like Social Security and
Medicare stay along with an increased
military spending. So the government
really stays a similar size. But before
I end this video, I want to mention that
this rise in conservatism was very
impactful, mostly because the 1980s
wasn't even that long ago. Modern
politics to this day still debate
ideologies from the 80s and beyond. And
also these conservative 80s weren't even
totally political. You will also see
evangelical Christians rise into
supporting and aligning with the
conservative side. So now it has a clear
social effect. Hey there. Do you
remember that whole Cold War thing that
has been going on for a while now? Well,
it actually is going to end in this
video with the collapse of the Soviet
Union. Now, really quickly, I want to
say that the dissolution of the Soviet
Union is a very complex topic and there
is way too many reasons for it. So, just
understand that this video might be an
oversimplification. But anyway,
historians often like to blame three
people for the Soviet Union's collapse.
Ronald Reagan, Pope John Paul II, and
Macy Gorbachov. For Reagan's side, the
US will build a massive military with
increased spending, focusing on
defending against nuclear missiles, and
the program here was called SDI, or the
nickname Star Wars. Reagan also pushed
strong anti-communist rhetoric, even
going as far to call the Soviet Union a
quote evil empire. In fact, let's roll
that clip. to ignore the facts of
history and the aggressive impulses of
an evil empire.
>> O apply ice to the burned area. My
goodness. And finally, the last thing
here is that Reagan eventually worked
with the Soviet Union in a series of
meetings to reduce tensions. But moving
on, for Pope John Paul II, he helped
push anti-communist beliefs in Poland
and ignited a massive solidarity
movement, which was a big blow to the
Soviet Union. But the final person here
and probably the most important is Macau
Gorbachov who was the leader of the
Soviet Union starting in 1985.
Basically, Gorbachov is not like his
predecessors. He was instead a lot less
strict. And by this point, the USSR is
struggling to keep up financially with
the US. In response, Gorbachov releases
government reforms that attempt to fix
society, but instead totally weaken the
Soviet government. And finally,
countries controlled under the Soviet
Union begin to break away until 1989
where the Berlin Wall officially falls.
And a few years later, the Soviet Union
collapses, ending the Cold War. So now I
want you to think about something. Since
there is no more USSR rival, the US is
going to be the most powerful nation in
the world. And after this, it's also
important to note the US is still going
to intervene around the world for
various reasons like peacekeeping and
regional conflicts. And now I am sure
you can imagine lots of different
debates about the US's role in the world
will start up. Lots of people throughout
the last century in American history
have been working in factories. I mean
it was the whole point of the guilded
age. But now with the cold war mostly
over, countries with a specific emphasis
on China are going to open up to trade.
So that begs the question, if it is
cheaper to globalize and pay Chinese
workers to produce goods rather than
paying a lot of money to American
workers, why the heck would any business
stay localized in America? And this will
lead to one of the biggest shifts in
world history called globalization where
businesses operate globally, meaning
companies can produce goods in other
countries and there is a big trade
increase. And pretty quickly looking at
the United States, factory jobs dry up
relatively quickly. And now you see new
age technology come out at a very
crucial point. So that means now after
the 80s the US job market will shift to
mostly encapsulate service jobs. Meaning
things like retail, healthcare, finance,
education or tech. This means how people
work, how businesses operate, and how
people communicate all drastically
change in a brief period. This also
means that labor unions dramatically
decline alongside factory jobs. And I
want to point out that this new
technology like the internet and
computers really does change everything.
For example, later you have social media
along with stuff like remote work
becoming a possibility. You also see a
spike in production because new
technology makes it so workers can
produce more in less time. But wherever
there is light, there is also darkness.
And here I want to talk about the bad
effects of this new generation. The
first here is that wages for middle and
workingclass Americans stagnated as most
economic gains increasingly went to
corporations in the top 1%. The second
thing here though is a digital divide
because I want you to imagine that lots
of older folks who aren't prone to
changing their ways or might not have
access to the new tech could potentially
not adopt the new technological changes.
So that means some people benefit a lot
from the new tech economy while many
others are left behind. That question,
do you like being cold? I personally
don't really like it and a lot of
Americans actually agree with me which
is why in the 1980s millions of
Americans will migrate to the sunb belt.
The reason being hotter temperatures and
opportunities which will cause these
regions to gain more political power.
But moving on after 1965 when that whole
immigration act was passed immigration
steadily rose following the '60s. But
then you see it spike like crazy in the
1980s. And this happens because of a
collection of things. The first thing is
that the US enacted the Refugee Act of
1980, which just simply adopted a
humanitarian approach to admitting and
resettling refugees. But the bigger
thing here is a whole lot of bad things
around the world happened all at once.
For example, Mexico and Cuba both go
through an economic crisis. El Salvador,
Guatemala, and Nicaragua all go through
civil wars. Communism will force
thousands to flee from Vietnam,
Cambodia, and Laos. And Iran also goes
through a revolution. And many people
also left the Philippines, Korea, and
India. Now, you don't need to
necessarily memorize these all. I just
want to show you that a lot of stuff
happened all at once, which caused so
many different immigrants to enter the
United States in the 1980s. The big
effect you see here is what our society
has become now in the present. America
is so culturally diverse as a country
that there are so many bilingual
communities and lots of culture from
other countries. I am sure you see all
over the place. And another big effect
of this is that immigrants will often
fill many bluecollar jobs, meaning
manual laborbased jobs in America. But
the other big thing this leads to is the
modern debates surrounding immigration.
Things like border control, legal versus
illegal immigration, bilingual
education, and the more complex
assimilation versus multiculturalism.
Welcome to the last topic of AP US
history in under 3 minutes. My intro
here will just be to simply say thank
you to you all for a wonderful year
together. And let's get into it. So, not
to be abrupt here, but 9/11, it is an
event we all know. Planes will crash
into the World Trade Center and the
Pentagon in a coordinated terrorist
attack carried out by the group
al-Qaeda. This is shocking to the US at
the time. And it is a very unprecedented
event. And so, the US response to this
will be to enact a war on terror. And if
you were like me and wonder how exactly
you can enact a war on an ideology, well
really what the war on terror was was a
war in Afghanistan [music] targeting the
terrorist group responsible for 9/11,
al-Qaeda, and the Taliban government
that supported the group. And also, the
war on terror expanded to Iraq, for
reasons originally justified by claims
of weapons of mass destruction. It's
also important to note that the US
depended a lot on oil coming from the
Middle East and so a lot of
complications arose over energy because
of the military actions happening in
that region. So the US shifts they don't
have cold war enemies anymore. Their big
enemy now is instead terror and this
will even expand to the homeront with
the Patriot Act where the US expanded
law enforcement surveillance powers and
strengthened measures against terrorism
financing. If you were a supporter of
this act, you might note the need to
keep Americans safe. But critics of this
act might say this violates civil
liberties and privacy rights. But
anyway, for one last time, let's look at
the US. What can we say at the end of
this course? Well, the US is the most
powerful nation in the world. That is
pretty objective. The US will continue
to intervene internationally, influence
global politics, and lead economically
and militarily. All right, everybody.
That is the entire A push course over.
Please do consider subscribing to my
non-educational channel and watching
this video which was a vlog I did on
that channel. Thank you all for being
with me this year. It has been a lot of
fun and I have enjoyed making these
videos quite a lot. That's all for me
though. Crush that exam and have a good
one everybody.